<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reformer rack'd: and his confession. Or, some observations upon the keeping the thirtieth of January, and twenty ninth of May, considered in a brief reflexion on the principles of his party in general, with some digressive touches upon the author's notion of those anniversaries. To which is added, A new discovery of Old England: written and privately printed in the time of Oliver's usurpation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28847</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825068</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207741</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264198604</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825068</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99825068e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1938:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reformer rack'd: and his confession. Or, some observations upon the keeping the thirtieth of January, and twenty ninth of May, considered in a brief reflexion on the principles of his party in general, with some digressive touches upon the author's notion of those anniversaries. To which is added, A new discovery of Old England: written and privately printed in the time of Oliver's usurpation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43, [3], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207741:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207741:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Reformer Rack'd:</hi> AND HIS CONFESSION.</p>
            <p>OR, Some Observations upon the keeping the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> and Twenty Ninth of <hi>May,</hi> considered: In a brief Reflexion on the Principles of his Party in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, with some digressive Touches upon the Author's Notion of those Anniversaries.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A New Discovery of Old <hi>England:</hi> Written and privately Printed in the Time of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Usurpation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Did I not more consider my Subject's Satisfaction than mine own Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, I should never have given the Malice of some Men that pleasure, as to see me take notice of, or remember what they say, or object. I would leave the Authors to be punished by their own evil Manners, and seared Consciences.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 118.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be sold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:207741:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207741:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Reformer Rack'd:</hi> AND HIS CONFESSION.</head>
            <p>THE strained weaknesses and fulsom unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comingnesses of <hi>Codrus</hi>'s Verse, must heighten the true Poet's Indignation; the very recital of them must <hi>whet</hi> his Noble Anger, and set a steeling <hi>Edge</hi> on the bluntest Ingenuity: So the sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Wit of a <hi>Novice,</hi> a <hi>Bavius</hi> or <hi>Maevius,</hi> hath been treated with nothing but Sarcasm and Satyr, Scorn and Proverb. As the Fooleries of Love, and the <hi>womanish</hi> Flatteries of Poetasters, have been always unsuccessful and contemptible, and ridiculous in an undegenerate Age of <hi>masculine</hi> Vertue; so the Smatterers in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie, and the unmanly poornesses of trifling Malice, or Presbyterian <hi>Cant,</hi> are not like to have better Fate, or hope to escape the <hi>Lash</hi> and <hi>Baffle</hi> of a <hi>Church-of-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland-Pen.</hi> How often the Non-con's have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered by our irrefragable Clergy, in Debates of this Nature, <hi>viz. Whether our Church-Ceremonies were super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious Relicks of Popery, absurd, and not to be endured?</hi> p. 2, 3. <hi>Whether Ecclesiastical Laws and Ordinances be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207741:3"/>or meer Human Invention, inconsistent with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Liberty, and are pure Will-Worship?</hi> p. 30, 32, 33. <hi>Whether the setting apart some Days for holier Ʋse and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is a Branch of Heathenism or Popish Idolatry? And appointing Anniversaries, Festivals and Fasts upon any Man's Account be Blasphemous, and derogatory to the Authority of the Lord of Sabbath?</hi> p. 27, 28, 29. themselves may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member who always came off with the <hi>Foil;</hi> and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks they might have learned from the Wraftling of <hi>Lincolns-Inn-fields,</hi> or from Shame, to have desisted, and flung off the Belt: But here's a doughty Antagonist hath a mind to Dispute it again, though he be sure to be worsted for his pains, and thrown out in the <hi>struggle:</hi> It is the Nature of a <hi>Fool-hardy</hi> Fellow, and more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Dick</hi> the Butcher than one of the <hi>Sober-Party,</hi> to run the Risque of a dozen broken Heads before he will lay down the Cudgel. I may relate, but never hope to Decide or Quell their refractory Animosities; and truly to recite all their <hi>Bear-Garden-Adventures</hi> against our Church, and their snarling Cavils against her Holy Sanctions and Wise Constitutions, would show the Reader how great a mind they have to make Schism but a more sanctified Sport, and to remove the Royal Diversions of Bull-Baiting and Bear-Baiting into the House of God. Those who Foster up Lion's Whelps and Foxes Cubs of Division within the Grates of their own Breasts, can as easily with the favour of the State and Press, turn the Temple of the Lord into an Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theatre of <hi>wild</hi> Divinity and savage Christianity, as transmography St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s into a Stable, and make it a <hi>Den</hi> of Filthiness and Horse-dung. The Levitical <hi>Augaeus</hi> was resolved to make Superstition stink, though his own Practice smelled strong of Bestiality for't; and surely he cannot call this a sweet Revenge upon <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207741:3"/>when he must necessarily hold his Nose for the Ho-go and Brutishness of his own Actions, and only Snivel out his hateful, <hi>hoggish,</hi> and nasty Reformation. Well then; <hi>Vexatus toties</hi> with <hi>Geneva-rant</hi> or <hi>Aetnean</hi> Eruptions and Distractions at home, I must now break out into <hi>Juvenal</hi>'s <hi>nunquamne reponam?</hi> Justice and Charity let the Author of those <hi>reproachful Observations</hi> upon the Martyrdom and Restauration, expect from an injured Loyalist and a disturbed Privado. He deserves to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered with the Severity of Truth and Law; his <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsgate</hi> Scold and Railery against our Pious Solemniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Fast and a Thanksgiving; the former upon a most dreadful and doleful, the latter upon a most joyful Account, requires the deepest Stab from a <hi>poyniarding</hi> Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility: He is troubled with that Distemper, the <hi>Choler</hi> of a passionate Folly, and Spleen of Malice, which Lenitives cannot Cure, and no <hi>Remedy</hi> can be worse than his <hi>Disease.</hi> If there be any secular Care of the Scepter, if any pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous regard for the Mitre, if there be any Security of their present Majesties, if any just yearly <hi>Tribute</hi> of streaming Tears be payable to the Blessed Memory of Massacred <hi>Charles,</hi> if any Anniversary Mean for a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal-barbarity, and the most Capital and Unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Offence to Majesty above our Terrestrial <hi>Turf,</hi> if any sincere Lamentation be due to the Funeral of a Martyr, if Oblivion must not shade his <hi>Hearse,</hi> if we must not Rhodomontade <hi>Heaven</hi> with our Innocence and Impunity in the matter, if we must not think to Trick and Bilk God's waking Vengeance, as a Cullied Coachman is sometimes served: If our Hymns and Songs of <hi>ecstasied Joy</hi> for those eminent Mercies and Blessings of God conferred on us in returning us King <hi>Charles</hi> II. again to the <hi>fade</hi> of a flourishing Usurpation, must not cease in our Choires: Then my Author's <hi>leaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:207741:4"/>may Commence a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> e're long to Love and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Honour and Honesty, Courage and Constancy in <hi>Palace-yard.</hi> Himself may save his Bacon, but the Flame perhaps will Singe and Smoak him a little, and <hi>J. G. G.</hi> will smell of Rank Faction and Anti-Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical <hi>Burnings:</hi> It was a bold Stroke of some disaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Poet or other to Acumen his Epigram thus upon the Pastoral Letter:
<q>Proh pia pompa rogi! proh gloria funeris! Auctor Non meruit fato Nobiliore mori.</q> That was too hard upon the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and the Sting is too sharp for my <hi>Author</hi>'s thin <hi>skinn'd Conscience.</hi> The Waggish Jacks were at that time mightily taken with the Pun, <hi>Burn-it, Burn-it,</hi> in Rythm to its Author, and thought I'le warrant ye, it hit <hi>Oliver</hi> a notable Box on the Ear for his <hi>Magna Charta, Magna Farta:</hi> But his Dissentership hath not been the subject of one <hi>Oxford</hi> Jest or Laughter yet, nor of a Parliamentary Curiosity and <hi>Criticism;</hi> to his chief Credit and Repute be it spoken. Revenge and Tears must burst hence from a compassionate and vexed Soul: The <hi>one</hi> to stop his foul Mouth against our Church <hi>appointment,</hi> and the Dead, which common <hi>Civility</hi> to a departed <hi>Soul</hi> might have done; and the <hi>Gag</hi> of <hi>Licensing</hi> one would have thought, might have silenced the notoriousest untruth, and <hi>disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuousness</hi> to both: The <hi>other</hi> to quench a flagrant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustion and <hi>glowing</hi> discontent, which no doubt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary thinks he hath sufficiently fired under the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre; our <hi>Guy</hi> may fancy he hath kindled Powder enough to Blow up a Thousand Churches that stand in his way of Levelling, or give a <hi>Rub</hi> to his Confusion-stratagem, and to make King <hi>Charles</hi> the First's Sacred Ashes to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207741:4"/>
               <hi>Caper</hi> in the Air, to <hi>blacken</hi> his embalmed Memory, or to <hi>Snuff</hi> a Stink of it into the Nostrils of Mungril-Loyalists, as much as Hellish Aspersions can <hi>Nauseate.</hi> His intentions surely <hi>Dance</hi> after <hi>Jack-Presbyter</hi>'s merry <hi>Bagpipe,</hi> to the <hi>Tune</hi> of Beheading, Demolishing, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, and all the ings and twangs of Clashing Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the established <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> No question but this new Fidling Modeller hath promised himself to Screw up his Humanity and Christian Goodness to a higher Pin, to a loftier Cut-throat Elah; and if times would serve his <hi>turn,</hi> to change this Fast into a Festival: If his Dissenting Discord and <hi>Schismatical Squeak</hi> would take, and tickle the Asses Ear to his Auditory, 'tis Cross and Pile whether the sweet Tantony-Pig-Israelite, would not leave his Whining Raptures, and Braying in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinarian Ecstasies, and then Sing us a joyful elevated <hi>Venite, Exultemus,</hi> instead of a sobbing Air, sad Obit, or mournful Ditty (as <hi>p.</hi> 22. he hints, <hi>our Psalms and Matins upon this occasion, are no Holier than Ballading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuff, or Bell-man's Anthem</hi>) for the horrid, barbarous, and deplorable Murther of our most Gracious, Learned, Pious KING. This is he that would <hi>Hallelujah</hi> his God for the most execrable Villany on the Thirtieth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary;</hi> and Veil <hi>White-Hall</hi> with a Mourning and Sable Hue, Weep, and bewail with a disconsolate Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the happy and peaceable Restoration on the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ninth of <hi>May.</hi> This is he that would have adorned the <hi>temples</hi> of that Head which the Predecessors of his Jack-Catch-Kidney cut off with Bayes, and have trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Equipage with Cypress, Owling with the hideous <hi>Screeches</hi> of Grief, that he should survive the Fate of a Martyr, or return in the Triumph of an Unanimous Joy, <hi>State,</hi> and loud <hi>Huz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zahs</hi> of his Welcoming Subjects. His whole Drift <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:207741:5"/>either totally to <hi>subvert</hi> our Ecclesiastical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or at least to <hi>invert</hi> the Decent Order and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Administration of it; and I cannot solve this Knot or Dilemma, whether he would throw the Church out at the Windows, or turn her admirable, not (as in his good natur'd <hi>Reveries</hi> and Enthusiastick Convulsion) superstitious Constitutions <hi>topsie turvy,</hi> like <hi>Passus</hi>'s Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Horse in <hi>Lucian,</hi> with its Heels up-bank; for he is very Angry that the People should be so much Priest-ridden, <hi>p.</hi> 9. It is a monstrous Imagination, or won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Fancy of his, to represent the Vicar and his Parish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioners as one great incorporated Centaur. 'Tis storied that <hi>Vannini</hi> had a wicked Design of insinuating that there was <hi>no God,</hi> by his weak proving that there was <hi>One;</hi> and of propagating as well as confirming Atheism, and a disbelief of a Deity, by his slender Arguments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for its Being and Existence: Our Pamphleteer is much in the same Predicament with this sly <hi>Pernicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so,</hi> though with a different Design perhaps; for he hath done his <hi>good Old Cause</hi> infinitely more <hi>hurt</hi> than <hi>good</hi> by his impertinent <hi>Ramble,</hi> and Cobweb-reasoning, which may Catch Flies, some silly Bigotted Zealots; but a Hornet must presently break thorough it, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of stronger Sense and abler Learning it can never <hi>hold</hi> or <hi>insnare:</hi> He hath taken a World of pains to Spin out the Thred of a <hi>sensless</hi> as well as <hi>breathless</hi> Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to inodiate our Reformation; but I must add to no greater purpose than to show us in effect, what Weak <hi>Hinges</hi> the Bosom-principles of their beloved Dissention, Singularity, and Peevishness do turn. My Author's dissembling <hi>Innuendo</hi>'s of his Charity, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that the Fact was an <hi>Horrid Murther, Execrable, as Black as Words can make it,</hi> p. 1. can be no <hi>Blind</hi> of his Obloquy and Calumny to the <hi>Eye</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207741:5"/>the unprejudiced World, after I have <hi>unmasked</hi> his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing</hi> of it, set his traducing indignities against the solemn Commemoration of it <hi>bare-faced,</hi> uncloathed the Wolf, and shown his true Complexion; for I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, he is an <hi>ugly-squinting-wide-mouth'd Fellow,</hi> as ever I met with in all my <hi>Pamphleteering</hi> Travels. Herein he deals with the Martyr like School-Boys; first he <hi>stroaks</hi> his <hi>grave Beard,</hi> Memory, and future Glories, declaring <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>That he believes God shewed him Mercy; that the taking away his Life was an ill thing; and that the loud and crying sin of Blood-guiltiness defiles a Land:</hi> He might have said, <hi>defiled this Land.</hi> But afterwards he is a Rogue and a Rascal, Arraigned by him as a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and <hi>Justice was executed upon the Guilty:</hi> Just so <hi>they Flauche</hi> and Cully their School-Fellows for a piece of <hi>Apple,</hi> or a <hi>play-thing: He's very apt, and hath his Acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at his Fingers-ends; and in the unsuccessful Event, they tell him he's a Jackanapes, and a Blockhead.</hi> How much <hi>Dust</hi> was beat out of the Cushion at St. <hi>Mary le Bow</hi> the last Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> to sully the Face of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr's Government, some of the August Assembly may be Conscious, if the Chair be Oblivious. With what a deal of irreverend Dirt was his fal'n Crown bespat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; such usage a disaffected Gentleman, or perjured Villain, may meet with from the Hands of the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>Mob;</hi> and it is merciful enough if the latter does not pay the Excise of his Ears too: But would one have thought such Kennel-indignities and Reproach, the very Ammunition of the Streets could be <hi>spewed</hi> up from the Mouth of a Man of God, on a Soveraign, whose Fall and Dissolution was Violent, Inhumane, Unnatural: His <hi>Sermon</hi>'s foul, and false Aspersions sound more like the Accents of Rotten Eggs than the Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of a <hi>Divine</hi>'s Compassion, or the humbling Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207741:6"/>of a Pulpit for a Sin that is not yet Dumb, but still groans out, and pronounces <hi>Wo</hi> unto us <hi>Achitophel's,</hi> that we have sinned, and us <hi>Shimei's,</hi> that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse we still Curse the King. Let me Query with him in his own phrase; <hi>Did that Prince hazard his Crown, not out of Charity to relieve his Country, but from a desire to oppress it, and so died the Martyr of his own Folly?</hi> p. 2. <hi>Was his decollation a Judgment brought upon him by his own Sins?</hi> p. 2. <hi>Was his Practice, or Course of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice like</hi> Jehoiakim's, <hi>which brought Ruin upon his own House, Misery upon his Kingdom, and Infamy upon his Name; insomuch that we ought by God's own Example, to forbid any Lamentation for his Death, or decent Burial to be bestowed on his Body?</hi> p. 9. <hi>Were Flatterers and Parasites his Favorites; or did he Crumble his People into Factions? Did that good and peaceable</hi> Josiah <hi>whet the Anger of</hi> Judah <hi>against</hi> Benjamin, <hi>or</hi> Benjamin <hi>against</hi> Judah? <hi>Was Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantry or Tumultuary Broils his Delight, or those Sins which were the Natural and Specifick Causes of that respective Punishment;</hi> or if I do not wrest his Sense, <hi>Was he a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch easily gullified, and ought to have had his Head in his Hand for being so?</hi> p. 4.17. <hi>Did he aspire to an Arbitrary or Despotick Tyranny, which began those Complaints, Heats, and Tumults in the Hearts of his Subjects; or was that Spark innocently and excusably kindled, which set the Nation on Fire, and which nothing but the Blood of their King could Extinguish?</hi> p. 22. This Point in former <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie,</hi> hath been so clearly given and determined against Mr. <hi>St—n's</hi> Sentiments, that <hi>Ben Johnson</hi>'s Inigo <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn's,</hi> squeeking <hi>it is not so,</hi> in a Dispute with his <hi>Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> in a <hi>Bartholomew-Fair,</hi> may be a very satisfactory and decisive Answer here. My Application of his hints is proper and natural, else he flourishes up a Discourse into Idea's of Scripture, and to apply them to any other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207741:6"/>times than those Chronicled of <hi>Josiah,</hi> is to <hi>Wiredraw</hi> them; and then the <hi>Anniversary Occasion</hi> is meerly No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and Chimerical, meaning no more of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Death, than of <hi>Sancha Pancha's</hi> being toss'd in a Blanket: Therefore whether he had rather be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured for <hi>impertinency</hi> and <hi>shuffling off</hi> the solemn occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and the Injunction of Holy Church; or Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niating and <hi>maligning</hi> that Prince's Actions, I leave him to choose: To play fast and loose with his Function, perhaps may be his <hi>interest,</hi> and interest his <hi>Oracle.</hi> His Living may be his <hi>Delphos,</hi> and Pluralities his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos,</hi> which the powerful <hi>Rhetorick</hi> of Satan <hi>staggers</hi> the Conscience to preserve, as the Devil acted in defence of his Oratory, when he raised a Tempest of Sand, and choaked those <hi>Persians</hi> therewith who were sent to over-turn the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Ammon, Ra. Hist.</hi> p. 384. What a noise of late, <hi>Pulpit-thumping</hi> hath made on Holidays, set times of <hi>Festivity, Fasts,</hi> and all so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Occasions, to <hi>deafen</hi> us that we should not hear the Sobs, Shrieks, and Sighs of a languishing and sinful Nation? What <hi>Odiums</hi> and Disparagement have been <hi>Pamphleted</hi> from the Press upon that King's Prudent Administration of Affairs, which had winded up both Church and State to an Eternal Settlement, if <hi>Matchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian</hi> Statesmen, and new Projectors of a Hydra-headed Government had not unraveled the whole <hi>Clue,</hi> to conduct themselves through the Labyrinth of their own crooked Fancies and Novelties, to King the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile or Multitude, and <hi>Crown</hi> their Soveraign Lord the People? And all this is harangued to <hi>depreciate</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of imbruing our Hands in the Blood of God's Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, by vilifying his Reason and Honour as a Man, his Religion and Virtues as a Christian, and his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and Justice to his Subjects as a King: For verily
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207741:7"/>to retort Mr. <hi>St—n's</hi> own Words, with a little varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon himself: <hi>He, while he seems to bewail the Wound, seems also to</hi> Justifie <hi>the Hand that Struck and gave it;</hi> or at least, not to be over-passionately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for his Death.</p>
            <p>This Digression is pardonable in all the Rules of <hi>Complaisance;</hi> for now I have shook Hands with my Author's Cousin German, and (may it please his Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship) would it not have been Rude not to have passed a Complement on so near a Relation of his by the way?</p>
            <p>However, let me avoid the wonted Fatigue and Prolixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Brothers of the Cloak, and the Cheveril-lung'd Tediousness of the <hi>Brawlers</hi> of the <hi>Amsterdam-Cut</hi> and <hi>Querpo,</hi> while I study <hi>Brevity;</hi> and I must Preface thus much to my Reader, that my intended Aim is as much to tread Antipodes to their <hi>long-windedness,</hi> as to their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Politicks; though to Counter-policy their plotting Policies, to <hi>Countermine</hi> their undermining Wheedle, Juggle, and <hi>Dark-Lanthorn-Contrivances</hi> against Kingly, as well as Church-Power, was a Task worthy a Man of Letters and Piety, a Province worthy Dr. <hi>Nalson.</hi> The obscure Stratagems of <hi>Tub-arians</hi> I hate, since GOD hath said <hi>Fiat Lux.</hi> How they have maliced us, and tricked us, one while Acting Comedians in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and <hi>Frothing</hi> Jack-Puddings <hi>Banter</hi> upon us; another while acting in good earnest Tragedians in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, <hi>dear-bought</hi> Experience hath taught us; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as not only the freedom and quiet, but the <hi>advancement</hi> of Presbytery to a <hi>topping</hi> Pitch, is the <hi>Mark</hi> which their Consciences, <hi>bent</hi> to the highest, <hi>shoot</hi> at, it will be no rash Confidence, or shrewd Conjecture in me to assign their Charity, Justice, and Truth no other Being, like the Philosophers <hi>Hircocervus,</hi> or <hi>first matter,</hi> but in <hi>Terms.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:207741:7"/>
            <p>I am amazed at the Negligence or <hi>Supineness</hi> of our most <hi>Orthodox Clergy</hi> at this Juncture; certainly they are not wrapt up in Gown and Cassock for Sleep and Repose: Were they the greatest <hi>Lurdans,</hi> methinks the <hi>Bawl</hi> of unlearned Opinions, and Scandalous both to the Palace and See, lately broached on the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> might have awakened them into a Militant Vigilance before <hi>May,</hi> and roused the <hi>Levitical Slug</hi> from Ease and Idleness, to have defeated the illiterate <hi>Force</hi> of a few <hi>Presbyterian Scriblers,</hi> before they should Form a more Numerous and Formidable <hi>Rapparism;</hi> if their <hi>Mobility</hi> once get a Head, it will be hard to disperse them: If an Enemy is suffered to come in upon us, he may easily Wrastle us into his Mercy, and the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Stander-by, may see us thrown at their Will and Pleasure into <hi>Socinianism, Arianism, Anabaptism, Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nism, Common-wealthism,</hi> or any other <hi>Heretical-ism,</hi> to the utter Abolition of our <hi>Communion,</hi> or downfall, ruin, and <hi>Rubbish</hi> of the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> as well as Ceremonies of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Devotion.</hi> With Joy and Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation I allow the great <hi>Daniel B</hi>—s, (his God's mighty intimate and Chrony, or Election-Huckster to his <hi>Cullied</hi> Disciples, for having made them Cry with the hard words of Hell and Damnation, he <hi>Spices</hi> their Tears with softer Language, and <hi>Sugar-plumbs</hi> the Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering Elect into Patience) the Liberty of Conscience; but let our Bishops and Pastors look to it, whether he, or some of the same Herd with that Bell-wether of Schism, makes Conscience of that Liberty. I do not deny those Spirits of Faction, the gracious and pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory Favour of the State; for that Power can only Exorcise, or lay the Legion thus: But then let their Preachments move within their own Orb, and the Sweet-Singer-of <hi>Israel Humm</hi> and <hi>Buz</hi> within his own
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207741:8"/>Sphere, and <hi>Sternhold</hi> it no further; for when an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious <hi>Genius,</hi> and a hot, aspiring, and <hi>flaming</hi> Perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion is emboldened, or hurried aside into an Eccentrick Motion, it is dangerous, and must, with <hi>Partridges</hi> leave, presage a <hi>Civil Combustion;</hi> and by the courteous Condescension of a State-Prophet, or Chimney-Augur, must foretell a <hi>smoaking</hi> disaster, and doleful Eclipse of the Radiant Meridian Lustre of the Gospel that shines now among us only with <hi>refracted</hi> Beams in <hi>England.</hi> Must we give ground to these Onsets though they be Frivolous? What a little <hi>scar</hi> or <hi>flaw</hi> in the Face hath turned to a Canker, so that <hi>Incisions,</hi> Amputations, and all the Skill of Chirurgery could not work the <hi>Cure?</hi> Must we give way to the Accomplishment of these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Gulphs or Chasms, and not retard the great Ends of little sly Designs? Trivial and Pigmy-means have executed the vastest and most Giant-intentions: And the most insignificant Creature a Pismire, could vent it's <hi>Spleen</hi> upon the Eagle's Eggs, even in <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Lap; we have the Moral here. Must we finally <hi>retreat</hi> into Silence? I hope it is but to <hi>Rally</hi> with powerfuller <hi>stress</hi> of Argument and Confutation; insomuch, that our Faithful Clergy in a total <hi>Rout</hi> of the <hi>Achilles,</hi> and all his <hi>Myrmidon's</hi> or <hi>Emmets</hi> of Presbytery, may be Crowned with the <hi>Trophies</hi> of Unity, Amity, Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and the Blessing of Peace; or, if this be too <hi>Hostile</hi> an <hi>Alarm,</hi> may they give 'em a more <hi>amicable</hi> Battel, and Accept the Dissenters, those <hi>Banditi,</hi> Moss-Troopers, and Rapparees of Religion, their Overtures or <hi>Capitulations</hi> for <hi>Surrendring</hi> themselves honourably to our Conquering Communion and Winning Liturgy. Then may Whig and Tory Kiss each other, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness and Peace will flourish in our Land. My greatest <hi>Ʋtinam</hi> is, that I were able to Book that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207741:8"/>
               <hi>Pacificatorium,</hi> or happy <hi>Eirenicon</hi> in these distract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed times, which might universally reconcile our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and <hi>heal</hi> our Breaches beyond <hi>Festering</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon these Considerations, I could not hold from <hi>wagging</hi> my <hi>Finger</hi> in this Quarrel; I have only played the Scout, I confess, and told the Army of our Church of the approach of an Enemy: Surprize is half a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. Though it be not the Province of a Lay-Man, yet may it Excite and <hi>Fan</hi> some Nobler Soul in our Hierarchy, to Breath out a warmer Discourse upon this Topick. What other Character can be given of the <hi>Capricio</hi>'s, Ignorance, Self-conceit and Love, Presumption and <hi>Bigotry</hi> of our Dissenting Brethren, but that they shufflle and <hi>pack</hi> all Religion and secular Rule up into sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Chimera's, subtile Maggoticism, zealous Phrensies or Whimsies, and have Cynical-Gnostical Idea's of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Spiritual <hi>Regimen.</hi> They are industriously busied Tooth and Nail, <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Tongue</hi>-concerned for a regulated Employment, and a just or holy Exercise of Gown and Sword; but then all is huddled together, <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium gatherum,</hi> into Confusion and Barbarism; and all our Chronicles can aver, how at last they were fain to leave the Reformed <hi>Hotch-potch</hi> they had made of Church and State in an indigested and chaos'd <hi>humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jumble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not long ago since our Nation was uncrowned, unmanned, and I may say, unchristianed too, and in a manner <hi>dis-elemented</hi> by those Brick-layers of <hi>Babel:</hi> The wisest of our Forefathers foresaw clearly then (and pray what should Infatuate or Blind their Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny?) that it was too weighty a Work for a Hub-bub of <hi>Massanello's,</hi> or Mob of Mechanicks, to New-vamp Monarchy and Episcopacy better. They aimed at some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207741:9"/>but the Lord knows what; for we had like to have disappeared, and Vanished into the Old Nothing and Disorder; yet at long-run, nothing but the Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Majesty in Misery and Exile,</hi> or a joynt Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Episcopal <hi>Fiat</hi> could reduce the City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey's Tolly-Polly, hoite cum toite-management of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, Exotick and Domestick Commerce, Protection, Subjection, Liberty, and Property, to pristine Beauty and Form: And He being Dead, yet <hi>speaketh,</hi> and most truly <hi>divined, That</hi> GOD <hi>would not suffer those long to prosper in their</hi> Babel, <hi>who Builded it with the Bones, and Cemented it with the Blood of their Kings,</hi> p. 241. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now what would these <hi>Mole-workers</hi> be at throwing up Dust and Mould in their Gracious Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Vineyard, to put out the Eyes of Justice in their <hi>Courts,</hi> (which for another reason, the Smart whereof such <hi>Eye-sores</hi> deserve to feel, is painted Blind) and of Religion, Conscience, and Prerogative in their Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals? How unable are the Arts and Abilities of Handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, the sagacities of the Fraternity of the sanctified Awl or Louse-stabbing-launce, the Qualifications of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Button-makers, and the Wits of the Company of inspired Manufacturers, to New-model this Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Government to compleater Perfection, or Consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Glory and Renown? In short, we are pester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Crowd of Busie-bodies, who are minded to <hi>Sow</hi> all the <hi>Tares</hi> they can in the Kingdom, and put us to the trouble of <hi>Weeding:</hi> Or, like Monkies, that steal away when they have broke those <hi>Glasses</hi> they cannot mend again, they do all the Mischief and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock</hi> in the power of a Hurly-Burly, fomenting <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, Piques,</hi> and <hi>Murmurings,</hi> and at last slingingly Sneak into an Auger-hole, Coblers-stall, or Loom-shop.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:207741:9"/>
            <p>'Tis true of the urgers of Tub and Table-end Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies what was otherwise applied, that they are the Phaetons of Mankind, who <hi>Fire</hi> that <hi>Nation</hi> which they would seem by their <hi>spiritful</hi> Emotions and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranguing Heats but to <hi>Warm.</hi> And sincerely I cannot esteem them the best affected People to this present Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, since, when their Republican Zeal is inflamed into Revenge, what can quench it, but the Blood of an Archbishop, and their King too: If their priviledges, inclosures, communities, immunities, or Libertinism be intrenched upon; if their Copyhold is <hi>touched</hi> never so slightly, like Tinder they take, and some of them have owned with abundance of <hi>Scotch-Eloquence,</hi> what Incentives have been <hi>ingled</hi> to them. <hi>Vid. Scot. Presb. Eloq.</hi> No Bishop, no King, is a <hi>Maxim</hi> might be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in indelible <hi>Purple,</hi> or never to be forgotten Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Gore in the Politick Diary of every <hi>British Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign.</hi> There are a sort of Antish Men always Piquing at the Bishops; <hi>They must not be the King's Creatures,</hi> p. 17. The Royal Ear must be Deaf to all humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses, but their own Clamorous, Treacherous, and <hi>Judas-salutes</hi> or Complements; whereas I never knew them Minions or <hi>Tools</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> but Episcopacy <hi>Nodded,</hi> and Monarchy was <hi>Crushed</hi> with its Fall, and Crumbled into a <hi>Democracy,</hi> or Committee of the least Safety and Preservation of publick Good.</p>
            <p>It is by these steps that Old Arts advance and <hi>picqueer</hi> to our Dementation and Overthrow; when Envy and Haughtiness seek <hi>innovations</hi> by Faction, and publish their inward frettings and <hi>gallish</hi> Commotions against the Annual Commemoration of the Notorious <hi>Murder</hi> of a Prince, have a care of dis-robing Majesty again, and bringing it in <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Pomp to the <hi>Block:</hi> An <hi>English</hi> Monarch should by a kind of Royal Sympathy,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207741:10"/>Tremble, Shrink, and <hi>Spurn;</hi> and his Crown Totter at the approach of a Regicide: And if <hi>Ludlow</hi> tread near upon the Heels of Regal Power or Presence, it is pity but he had his Teeth or Brains dash'd out of his Head for his <hi>murthering</hi> Audacity. Such Villains have <hi>Scaffolds</hi> erected in their Breasts, and if Colour and Occasion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themselves fairly, they are presently screwed up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Whitehall-gate</hi> too: Some of the same 48-<hi>Coyn-Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors,</hi> and Rebellious Traytors, could with Heart and Hand <hi>Prologue</hi> to the like Bloody Tragedy anew, under the <hi>gulling</hi> Pretence of reforming Religion and Policy, and God knows in what King's Reign we might sing the Epilogue or <hi>Chorus</hi> the Exit. I much question whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Axe</hi> be yet laid aside since my Author would have us to forget and forgive that fatal <hi>Blow</hi> before time hath <hi>rusted</hi> the Weapon that gave it, and made us all truckle to Cruelty and a State of Force, as if the Loyal Cavaliers had all had but one Neck, and <hi>Nero</hi> had exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted his Wish: And does he <hi>crotchet</hi> that five and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years are sufficient to <hi>Stanch</hi> the Issue or Sea of that <hi>Royal Blood?</hi> My Veins tell me without Lunacy, it still <hi>flows</hi> upon this Nation, and threatens it with a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge</hi> of Destruction; and what can keep it at an Ebb, or divert the Menaces of Calamity from inundating upon us, but Fasting and Prayer? What can <hi>stemm</hi> it but the exorated Mercy of an Almighty? Does he think Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, and the memory of his Decollation ought to have <hi>expired</hi> with the King on the Theatre of his Death, or that the Sin crying for Vengeance, and no sooner committed, but recorded in the <hi>Rolls</hi> of an Omnipotent Fury, should be <hi>staged</hi> over only in Shew, and no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a <hi>Play-house-reality?</hi> Ought GOD's Anger and his Princely Innocence to have been buried together in the Grave of an ignoble <hi>Oblivion?</hi> How should we <hi>wipe</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:207741:10"/>off that <hi>Stain</hi> of so deep a <hi>Dye,</hi> when the Abettors of that Murder lewdly touch his sacred Tomb, and their <hi>guilt</hi> of inhumanity makes him <hi>bleed afresh?</hi> How should we asswage that Sin's <hi>deep-mouth'd roar</hi> for Punishment and Epidemical Penalties, when Fanatical Billows do but Swell the <hi>Tide</hi> and Rage of it higher? Is Behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a King no Barbarity, killing him a malignant, no Murder? From such Principles <hi>Libera nos Domine;</hi> and he that denies this Litany, is not to be confuted without a Rope, or convinced till he comes to a Tyburn-confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; and how should he have the benefit of Old Neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saving-Legit for such an Offence, when at the same time he denies Scripture, and renounces his Faith with God and his King? But our Author <hi>Opinionates,</hi> that Tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passes of the <hi>first magnitude</hi> might be forgotten as well as Petit Injuries forgiven? Is a King a Mushroom that <hi>grows</hi> up in a Night, and must be <hi>pickled</hi> in his own Blood the next Morning? Or if you bid him Good Morrow, must he be <hi>lopt</hi> off in the <hi>dawn</hi> of his Youth? Is he like an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sect</hi> of some few Warm and <hi>Calm</hi> Days duration, but a <hi>Storm</hi> comes, and then he no sooner <hi>Dies,</hi> but he must be Rotten too, and the Memory of him ought to be but an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, forgotten, and <hi>annihilated</hi> as soon as he is <hi>dissolved</hi> and <hi>interr'd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this Period my Author may think I should reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my self with one of his lusty <hi>Humphs;</hi> and give him leave to turn the <hi>Hour-glass</hi> of his Life, and <hi>Lownry</hi> once again: And so I do, Good-fellow, as often as he pleases. But I must now descend to Particulars, and consider his Observations more concisely and a <hi>propós. Every Thirtieth of January doth renew his thoughts yearly upon the occasion of that day;</hi> and surely puts him all in a <hi>pother:</hi> He is almost out of Breath at first <hi>Start,</hi> and Salutes the World <hi>puffing</hi> and Blowing with two Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207741:11"/>Winds of Doctrine. <hi>The thing,</hi> says he, <hi>hath two several Aspects.</hi> He always Things the <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> just as Men do <hi>that</hi> in Conversation which they hate to <hi>Name.</hi> However well spied, <hi>Janus;</hi> this is the Luck of having <hi>two Faces:</hi> Hypocrisie is Cat-eyed, and sees <hi>nine ways</hi> at <hi>once. For either it looks upon the Act of some Men against the living, or upon what others have done, and still do for the Dead: The former is unlawful, and the latter contrary to true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, Why Unlawful? It vexes his Righteous Soul, and exasperates his Spirits to an Inveteracy against, and hatred of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> to be told from it of the <hi>Failings</hi> and Cruelties of his Party, as much as a Sermon against <hi>High-Commoding</hi> and <hi>Top-Knotting, stomacks</hi> my <hi>Lady-all-pride:</hi> It touches him in the most <hi>sensible</hi> part, and Wounds him in an Old <hi>Sore;</hi> it makes the Gall in his Ears overflow; and do you think Christianity can <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie</hi> him into the harmlesness of a Dove, or that he is as <hi>mauped</hi> as a Stoick or Apathist, not to be incensed if you disgorge his loathsome Actions, and Spit the <hi>Filth</hi> of his own Principles in his <hi>Face?</hi> He hath a <hi>Magazine</hi> of <hi>Blocks, Halters</hi> and <hi>Gibbets</hi> for such <hi>Consecrated</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, or Church-bred Rudenesses; and the Parson may read a Wish in his <hi>Physs,</hi> that he could Hang him with his <hi>Looks.</hi> Do we imagine he should esteem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self a welcom Guest, or that a Hospitable Roof under which his National Crimes are always <hi>tauntingly</hi> thrown in his Dish, and he is uncharitably asked, what his <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal-Appetite</hi> says forsooth, to a King's Head for the last Course? Alas for the mischievous adage! <hi>Senes bis pueri,</hi> and the <hi>gray-headed-Child,</hi> or <hi>hoary Elder-sprig</hi> is <hi>bug-beared</hi> away from our Church with Raw-Head and Bloody bones. Is not all this unlawful? Are not such harsh and unpleasant Practices to be revenged of with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207741:11"/>Schism and Faction? Are not those Pulpit-Panegyricks on King CHARLES's memorable Vertues and <hi>Invectives</hi> against the Regicide, enough to <hi>unsheath</hi> the Civil Sword, and set the whole Kingdom at <hi>Daggers-drawing?</hi> Well, since he despairs of Reforming our Oratories from such <hi>netling</hi> Harangues, his resolve is to be no longer an any-thing-Arian, but a <hi>thorow-pac'd</hi> Dissenter; Such a Revenge I remember a certain Town-fool hath always in his Mouth, if any of his <hi>Allowance-masters</hi> or <hi>Almoners</hi> vexeth him, he will not come to his <hi>Doors</hi> for a Week afterwards; <hi>He'll fit him there.</hi> But hark, our Master of Reason! <hi>It were better to forget those things than to renew the Memory of them, which continues Divisions.</hi> Is this Christian Logick; were it better to wrap up our Gospel-talents in an idle Napkin of Silence and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, than to Preach and Evangelize the <hi>Jews</hi> out of the Pale of the Christian Church? The <hi>Sequel</hi> is, we must never hope to <hi>Proselyte</hi> them by Reproof, or tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them of their Sins. Unity in Religion sounds much of Heaven, its Harmonious Hierarchy, and the Bliss of Souls-separate; it <hi>Images</hi> GOD to us on Earth, and our Church might have shown as fair a Stamp of that <hi>triumphant</hi> Glory and Celestial Amity as any in <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> if the irreconcilable <hi>Vagaries,</hi> gross-carnal Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and intestine <hi>Contrasto's</hi> of such Whimsical Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onaries, as he, had not <hi>mangled</hi> and Scarr'd the Beauty of her Holiness, had not <hi>Split</hi> her into Divisions and Subdivisions, to the <hi>Wreck</hi> of the precious Cargo of her Unity and Purity, and made her altogether <hi>Militant</hi> with the Fry of Sectaries. The <hi>Division</hi> he imputes to the <hi>keeping</hi> an <hi>Anniversary,</hi> is an <hi>Idol</hi> of his own making and continuance, and he meerly slaves himself with Bandying about his own Principle. Novelty is the <hi>Dalilah</hi> he Hugs and Embraces till he's betrayed into
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207741:12"/>Division and Weakness, and then the <hi>Sampson</hi>'s strongest Efforts cannot <hi>shoulder</hi> down our Church.</p>
            <p>He Cries out against Divisions and giving Offences, as the Impudentest Crack about Town usually Exclaims, Lord! The Impudence of some Women! When no Brothel-House-Pander is able to Match Pimping and Prostitution with her. It is the Bawd's own Jealousie that makes her cry Whore first. What Divisions can this Day of Humiliation enlarge or continue, but <hi>those</hi> the Espousers whereof dethroned and vanquished Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty to a Grave, sacrificed it to Popular Fury, and left the Sin of their Victory <hi>unsubdued,</hi> and their Rebellious Error <hi>unrecanted</hi> by some of their Posterity to this day? Would they revoke that signal Wickedness, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate their Repentance with an Equal Popularity, they should <hi>Confederate</hi> their Prayers with us, to depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the respective Punishment and Vengeance of it. 'Tis true, the most Languishing Devotions and Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory <hi>Sighs cannot restore to Life, or remedy what is past;</hi> the <hi>weeping</hi> of a <hi>Jesus</hi> could only give poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> a Glorious and Extraordinary Resurrection on Earth: But our <hi>Tears</hi> somewhat sincerer than the Crocodile's, may perhaps Avert the Judgment which hath not yet discharged its self in <hi>Plague</hi> or <hi>Fire</hi> upon the present Fautors of that Rebellion, the <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and very <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile</hi> of our Divisions: <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> I say; and the belief of a Wrath impending, like <hi>Democles</hi>'s Sword, must be the chief Spell against our further <hi>Incantation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Head was severed from his Body, and not with <hi>Peleus</hi>'s <hi>Hasta</hi> that could Wound and Heal; I wonder at my Author's Plain dealing here among all the Salvo's of <hi>Commonwealth-Laws,</hi> that he does not play the <hi>Sorcerer</hi> with us, or give us a touch of his <hi>Medea</hi>'s Skill, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207741:12"/>say he was only killed like <hi>Aeson,</hi> to <hi>renew</hi> his declining <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Regal Vigour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But after Acts of Oblivion for such things are passed, the memory thereof ought to be forgotten,</hi> p. 2. Is he assured that that Act is <hi>ingrossed</hi> in the Book of Life, or that an Omniscient Mercy hath Recorded our Indemnity? By what Angel, and to <hi>whom</hi> below was the Bill Winged down, and our Pardon delivered? How neatly would he plead Prescription to God's Justice at the highest Tribunal, against the Penalty of a Sin, or in an <hi>Arrest</hi> of Judgment, and to stay its <hi>infliction?</hi> What a <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster-madness</hi> is this to pretend an Injunction against the Proceedings of an Invisible and Incontroulable Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature? Must we presumptuously <hi>fobb</hi> a <hi>forgetfulness</hi> upon the Mercy-seat above? Such an impenitent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption or Demurrer is most likely to hasten the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of GOD's Wrath and Justice. What! Are Five and Forty Years, or a Thousand, (which are to him but as one, and the shortest day in thy Almanack) time out of Memory with Heaven and its Omniscience? Certainly National Punishments are Relative to, and intailed upon National Sins; and what should cut off that <hi>entail</hi> from our otherwise forlorn Posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but a solemn Anniversary Repentance, and a repeated Renunciation of those Religious Divisions which tinctured and imbrued the <hi>Hands</hi> of their pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Fore-elders in the <hi>Sanguine</hi> Laver of Cruelty? The River <hi>Lethe</hi> cannot take out the Stains of their Honour and Perswasion. <hi>A penitent Revocation</hi> of their mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Politicks, must <hi>un-negro</hi> and <hi>dealbate</hi> their <hi>grim</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and nothing else can <hi>blanch</hi> o're the <hi>blots</hi> in the Escutcheon of their Convert-Assemblies. No; how fain would the <hi>Pilate wash</hi> his Hands of Innocent Blood, and forget the dictates of his own Conscience to please
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207741:13"/>a party? Is the Sin <hi>expiated;</hi> is the Crime <hi>attoned</hi> for? or that Butchery of the Prince of our Worldly <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>darling</hi> of our Church's <hi>militant success</hi> and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Felicity (who had no more Justice than the Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles allow a Calf, or the Slaughter-House an Oxe) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given? Must we now let him lye <hi>buried</hi> with the Burial of an Ass, and not Eccho his Obsequies down to coming Loyalty? Must <hi>lying Infamy,</hi> and some Men's foulest Obloquies deface his best Features, deform the most Beautiful of <hi>his</hi> Actions, or Contempt and Forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness stick upon his Blessed Memory? Must future Ages have no Nobler Tradition of <hi>his goodness</hi> and <hi>justice,</hi> than what the bitter <hi>Sarcasm</hi> or old taunt of <hi>Execution</hi> can convey to them, or <hi>immortalize, — Satia te sanguine, Cyrequem fitisti?</hi> Hitherto my Author hath been making his Pastime, or a <hi>Game</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Death, and the <hi>upshot</hi> is, that <hi>its enough once for all really and heartily to have done:</hi> His Tongue-ty'd Malice would not let him speak out <hi>to have celebrated the Martyrdom with a Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional remembrance;</hi> after that it degenerates into <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality</hi> and <hi>Foppery.</hi> This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of our mighty-regenerate, and a would-be-Puritan: If he once makes us Formalists in Divinity, we are his Lads of Wax, and our next Impression shall be <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he prescribes the Performance for our Dead Soveraign; and makes no more of his Government, Actions, <hi>Suspiria Regalia</hi> in Troubles, <hi>Tragical</hi> Sufferings on the Stage of his Life, or Memory of all this than of a Play or Noisy Farce, which never took in the <hi>Pit</hi> or <hi>Gallery</hi> of the World, and being once <hi>damned</hi> is never to be <hi>acted</hi> over again. But why once for all, why so precise and punctual to Unite? The most effectual method he can take to make us leave swallowing For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities, Superstitions, and drinking those Dregs of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207741:13"/>Popery (as he mis-calls our Ceremonial Worship) will be the same way the <hi>Grocer</hi>'s Boy is Cured of his Eating Plumbs, when we have had our <hi>Belly full of them:</hi> Let him take <hi>Selden</hi>'s <hi>probatum</hi> for't. As for him, we never hope to see his Covenant-maw cloyed with Seditious Doctrines, He digest Novelties so fast, and loves <hi>Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> so well.</p>
            <p>I wonder his <hi>Perswasion</hi> like his <hi>Palate,</hi> should not Relish any thing <hi>Twice</hi> which he grants to be <hi>Whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some</hi> and Innocent <hi>once,</hi> but <hi>Extempore Repetitions,</hi> and Fulsom Tautologies, wherewith their whole Service is stuffed like Beef, and larded like Bacon; the same thing <hi>over</hi> and <hi>over</hi> through the whole <hi>Piece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>It is contrary to true Religion to keep the Thirtieth of</hi> January: This is the <hi>Scare-crow</hi> that keeps the Rook our of our <hi>Vineyard.</hi> First our Church's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments and Solemnities widen the <hi>Breach</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Union, and then we run quite counter to the whole <hi>Tenure</hi> of true and sound Religion; just as a Nurse cries to the Child, <hi>pah, pah,</hi> when she would not have it touch a thing it hath a mind to Eat; so he frights his <hi>Infant-Converts,</hi> telling 'em they must not go to the Church, there's no good Food for their Souls; whereas perhaps neither of them could study or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe a more suitable and salutary Repast for either Constitution. This grand <hi>Charge</hi> he groundlesly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to bring us down to his <hi>Lure;</hi> and does he think we hover in an <hi>Airy</hi> Religion, and are to be inveigled and captivated, like a Company of silly giddy Larks? Are we turned like <hi>Weather-cocks,</hi> with an empty Puff of Doctrin? Is our Faith as unstable as <hi>Rushes,</hi> not to abide the weakest Shock and Gale of a Discourse <hi>unsha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken?</hi> Surely himself could have no good Opinion of such easie Proselytes. Fly Irreligion and Idolatry; this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207741:14"/>
               <hi>Call</hi> sounds sweetly, like the <hi>Hyaena</hi>'s Voice if it were not counterfeited, to allure us out of the Church and the <hi>Grotto</hi> of our Peace, to the Destruction of Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Power and Tranquility; if her ravishing Intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments call forth the <hi>Shepherd,</hi> she <hi>devours</hi> him in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy,</hi> and then the <hi>Orphaned Flock</hi> must go astray.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles,</hi> with a judicious Foresight, hath given a brave Counter-Cuffe to our <hi>round-head-Disputant</hi> in his Meditation upon the Ordinance against the Common-Prayer-Book. Here's a <hi>Rowland</hi> for his <hi>Oliver: It is no News to have all Innovations ushered in with the Name of Reformation in Church and State by those who seeking to gain Reputation with the vulgar for their extraordinary Parts and Piety, must needs undo whatever was formerly set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led never so well and wisely.</hi> And the Words of a King, a Scholar, and an Orator, upon the specious <hi>Reformations</hi> of those Times, must pierce him to the <hi>Bowels</hi> of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and hypocritical Pretensions. <hi>What Dissolutions of all Order and Government in the Church; what Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Schisms; what Ʋndecencies and Confusions in sacred Administrations; what sacrilegious Invasions upon the Rights and Revenues of the Church; what Contempt and Oppressions of the Clergy; what injurious Diminutions and Persecutions of me have followed (as Showers do warm Gleams) the Talk of Reformation, all sober Men are Witnesses, and with my self, sad Spectators hitherto?</hi> And do you know <hi>Hercules</hi> by his <hi>Foot</hi> again, or a Lion by his <hi>Paw?</hi> He hath sent his Book abroad as a <hi>Jackall,</hi> and only wants to <hi>grasp</hi> his Prey: If we will become his dearly beloved, he will preach <hi>Mince-Pies</hi> and <hi>Custards</hi> to his Babes of <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Grace,</hi> and hugg us; but then; just as the Monkey does her young ones, squeeze us to Death and <hi>Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> at last. How should we <hi>pin</hi> our <hi>Faith</hi> upon his <hi>Sleeve,</hi> or hang it upon that Cloak, and <hi>hope</hi> to scale
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207741:14"/>the <hi>Battlements</hi> of Heaven, when <hi>Bur—ss</hi> tells us it is so easily <hi>unbuttoned,</hi> and then we drop the Lord knows whither, not into a <hi>Saw-pit,</hi> but a bottomless Hell? Then we must take an eternal Swing of falling, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go a worse <hi>Agony,</hi> and have <hi>harder Language,</hi> or a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler <hi>Bruit</hi> than we had in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Den.</hi> His Party rails against our Church-Power as my Tippling <hi>Hostess</hi> does against <hi>Caudles</hi> and <hi>Burnt-Claret</hi> that comes a Day after the Gossipping <hi>Fare,</hi> and can get none of it; for I am of the Lord <hi>Lauder dal</hi>'s Opinion, That we might stop any of their <hi>mouths</hi> with a Bishoprick. Himself talks as much of Religion and our Differences, as the Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly Bully does of Roaring, Hectoring, and Fighting, and much to the same <hi>Humour;</hi> for neither of them do ever lend a <hi>Hand</hi> to decide a Quarrel, or endeavour a <hi>Pacification,</hi> so long as they carry off the <hi>Spoil;</hi> and accommodating the Matter is the least to their Interest, or <hi>Booty</hi> of Pick-Pocketting and Sharping: Yet this I must say for the Champion of Dissention, that he is no Coward or Faint-Heart; for seeing our Church-men together by the Ears about <hi>Stating</hi> the Controversie of Schism and Allegiance, our Adversary fairly and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageously steps up between 'em, and hits 'em both a Box on the Ear, and is resolute in the Scramble to carry away the Bone; and he may call them Mastiffs of Law and Divinity, if he please, I am afraid e're long they'll both be upon the Bear. I would fain know how his <hi>Conventicle-Religion</hi> comes to be the best, purest, and most <hi>Evangelical.</hi> Is it so fine because it hath <hi>stood</hi> his own Apostolical <hi>Test</hi> or <hi>Refining,</hi> and is of his own Phrantick Brain's <hi>Coining?</hi> I had like to have said <hi>Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> too; for he Dutchifies it, and <hi>lops</hi> off all <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> as superfluous Branches, or <hi>Prunes</hi> it of all <hi>sapless</hi> Decencies; but I think he hates Circumcision, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207741:15"/>such Ceremonial Trumperies of the Old Law. I could never yet believe the Herald to be the best Gentleman, because he makes his own Pedigree: And the curious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Blazonry of his Coat shall not convince me of his <hi>Extraction's</hi> being the most Illustrious; I always suspect this Bravo's Escutcheon and Gentility of Descent, and that Man's <hi>Geneva-Bounce</hi> or <hi>Comment</hi> upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his own Profession.</p>
            <p>To prove the Antiquity of their <hi>Presbytery,</hi> they mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpret the word Presbyter in the Fathers, and wrest their Sense to make their Profession venerable for its Oldness; so he that delights in Opticks would perswade us, that when <hi>Julius Caesar</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> he had Perspective-Glasses, because it is said, <hi>Positis Speculis:</hi> Whereas nothing was meant but his Watch or Sentinel that discovered how the Land lay: We are apt to strain any thing to the most <hi>incredible</hi> Sense that makes for our Opinions, though the <hi>intrinsick Truth</hi> of it be most incompatible with our Inventions and Practices; which is the very Fountain-head of Vulgar Perswasions and Errors: Quote the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) out of the most fictiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous History, and it sufficiently grounds our Belief of the fabulous Generation of <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Helena</hi> out of an Egg, whereas the Word among the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> had the Signification of an <hi>upper Room</hi> only, where they were born and brought up. So let us suppose, for example, the Word <hi>(Egg)</hi> in a Text of Scripture, the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an would interpret it an <hi>Hen-Egg</hi> or <hi>Goose-Egg,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be sure such an <hi>Egg</hi> as most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elish</hi> of his Perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, Novelty, or Spirit and Pleasure of contradicting another human <hi>Gloss.</hi> As for the divine Right and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of their modern Presbytery, Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> faceti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and comically <hi>table-talks</hi> him thus. <hi>When the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were sent to the Assembly concerning the</hi> Jus Divinum <hi>of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207741:15"/>Presbitery; their asking Time to answer them was a Satyr upon themselves: For if it were to be seen in the</hi> Text, <hi>they might quickly turn to the Place and shew us it. Their delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to answer, makes us think there's no such thing there. They do just as you have seen a Fellow do at a Tavern-reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he should come to pay his Reckoning, he puts his Hands into his Pockets, and keeps a grabling and a fumbling, and shaking, at last tells you he has left his</hi> Money <hi>at home; when all the Company knew at first, he had no Money there, for every Man can quickly find his own Money.</hi> He and I have both our Religion no doubt; and like a <hi>Fashion,</hi> he wears his Doublet Plain, I mine Fringed: We have both a Doublet, that's plain; we differ about Trimming. It is strange, that we should <hi>Rend</hi> and <hi>Tear</hi> our Saviour's Garment into so many Scraps and Pieces as are Cabaged from a New Suit of Cloathes, and all upon the Account of the Figure and Mode of Professing it seemless, and unjustly parted. Is it Taylor's work to take Measure of our Souls, or alter and decide our Religion, because we are utterly at odds about the <hi>Shape</hi> of it? Surely nothing can sit well or handsomly upon such <hi>monstrous, jarring,</hi> and <hi>un-sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrous</hi> Members.</p>
            <p>Will they still persevere in ignorant Obstinacy, and differ from us in Religion and Unity of Performance with the same Singularity as they do in their Habits; and with less Reason too? Will not this suffice, that it is not <hi>A-la-mode du Paree,</hi> except it be of a <hi>Geneva-Starchtness,</hi> and as stiff from <hi>Bowing</hi> to the Altar, and Complying with our Ceremonies, as the Inflexible Old Sultan in <hi>Tapestry-Stature?</hi> None of us believe the Altar to be God, or a <hi>Wooden Deity,</hi> any more than he believes the Carnal <hi>Anthropomorphitry</hi> of him. He
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207741:16"/>can <hi>Duck</hi> and <hi>Bow,</hi> and make his <hi>Honours,</hi> as well as any Master of Ceremony among us, to secular Grandeur and Quality; and why not to the God of his Worship in any Place, or at any Time, in Reverence to his Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presence? Yes; but <hi>the People of</hi> England, <hi>like those of</hi> Athens <hi>in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s days, in this thing of the Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are too Superstitious;</hi> and he gives us the <hi>Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Height</hi> of an aggravated Reason for't: <hi>In that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice we pray to God he will be pleased to give us the Grace to follow that Man's Charity and Patience; surely in this we are too Superstitious. Now time, place and service being appointed, next thing for us to do will be to Pray to him.</hi> How gladly would he <hi>malice</hi> us into Popery? <hi>Humane Literature</hi> always honoured Good Men, and Noble He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, with an Apotheosis after their <hi>Departure;</hi> but the Man of Letters tells us, Poetry is Popery: Surely he judges by the Ear, and it is a good one that never mistakes the <hi>Jangling</hi> of a pair of <hi>Tongs,</hi> for the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical Sound of the <hi>Harp-sicles.</hi> His <hi>Organ</hi> is mightily indisposed, and his <hi>Perception</hi> is false; he talks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Book, as the <hi>Blind-Fidler</hi> plays <hi>Tunes.</hi> Every word <hi>Montross</hi> wrote with his <hi>Swords point</hi> on the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>Charles,</hi> was Popery. Why so? He <hi>Trumpets</hi> the King's Praise and Eulogy to the World, and sounds an <hi>Alarm</hi> in the Ears of our Preacher of the Gospel of Peace; and would not this even make a Cur <hi>Whine,</hi> and shake his Head? This is it provokes him to <hi>grin</hi> and <hi>bark</hi> out Popery, Popery. We cannot talk of him by way of Eminence and Excellence of a Crowned Dignity; but we forthwith Canonize him, and Calendar him for a Saint, and that's Popery with a Witness: After this rate, a Ladies Beauties must not be commended, lest he twit us with <hi>Romish</hi> Adoration
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207741:16"/>for our Encomium's, whereas no question but the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Letcher could smuggle up a Buxom Sister with his Holy Kisses, and Vow his closer Embraces and Debauch as <hi>Consecrated</hi> as any Priest of 'em all; so his Crape in a Corner be not Babylonish: That's the Whore he would have Carted. But anon we shall Pray to Saint CHARLES: Yes, to be sure when he draws up the Form. Shall we not have Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship too? We have a great many <hi>Joynt-Stools</hi> in our Churches. In a short time a <hi>Yull-Clog</hi> or a <hi>Cart-Wheel</hi> shall not lye by us, but in his <hi>mendacious</hi> Construction we must pay our Devotions to it.</p>
            <p>The Countrey-man in <hi>Spain</hi> would not Pray to St. <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Image, because he knew it was made of his own Plumb-Tree; and can his Scholarship believe our Clergy ignoranter than that <hi>Rusticity,</hi> to Pray to and Adore a mouldring Carcass, or the curiousest Statue? He may as well report to the World that we <hi>Leg,</hi> and <hi>Knee</hi> St. GEORGE upon <hi>Horse-back</hi> at every Sign-post, or that we Kneel down at <hi>Charing-Cross,</hi> or <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> drop a Bead there, and mutter an AVE for the whole Lump of Brass. If he can pre-engage a transmarine Credulity, he may out-do <hi>Lucian</hi>'s <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Vera</hi> with his prolifick Invention of Figment against our <hi>Worship,</hi> and never fear to come to his ingenuous Confession of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as long as his single Authority can make it pass for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Truth.</p>
            <p>This were a Lie, and an <hi>Abuse</hi> within the <hi>Verge</hi> of the Court; and those who insinuate such clam-Romance, would scandalize our Prelacy, and <hi>inodiate</hi> it to the Lowns of the Kirk and Covenant: This Charge is just as unreasonable and foolish as heretofore Images were
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207741:17"/>called Mammets, and Adoration of 'em Mammetry; (Contractions for <hi>Mahomet</hi> and Mahometry) odious Names indeed, and scandalous; when all learneder Heads knew the Turks were forbidden Images as much as Wine by their Alcoran: So the Laws of our Church severely prohibit Idolatry and Superstition and Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and notwitstanding he says we are all the three, Idolaters. Superstitionists, Blasphemers: Who will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him then? Is he lunatick, and must we every <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi>-Moon be carressed with his Palmerine-Relations, and <hi>madly misrepresented</hi> with his <hi>Bedlam</hi>-Observations? We shall not <hi>chat,</hi> write from the <hi>Press,</hi> or <hi>preach</hi> from the Pulpit; but he'll be proclaiming <hi>War</hi> against us for Popery, and <hi>Canonading</hi> our Church with all the <hi>Railery</hi> and <hi>Artillery</hi> of Presbytery. No, we shall not walk the Streets e're long, but we shall vent Popery at the other <hi>End</hi> too, and this Fellow will be crying out upon the Stink, when the sweet Savour is all the while under his own Cloak, just as you see one beat a <hi>Dog</hi> out of the room for what is in his Breeches. If we eat <hi>Plumb-Pudding</hi> and <hi>roast-Beef</hi> in a Cooks shoop, he'll perhaps call it a Papistical Ordinary; and, if the Fit of Enthusiasm take him, he'll not spare to stay our Stomachs with tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us we <hi>feast</hi> and gormondize on our Saviour: And, <hi>Sacrament,</hi> we hold Transubstantiation in the <hi>Sir-Loin.</hi> But to leave such Hoghen-Errantry and Vagaries; a Voider for his Non-sense or Foolery: It is time to take it away. Is it an <hi>irreligious Petition</hi> we put up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Grace to follow King <hi>Charle</hi>'s Exemplary Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Patience? Mark his Charity in his Heavenly Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies: <hi>I bless God, I pray not so much that this bitter Cup of a violent Death may pass from me as that of his Wrath may pass from all those, whose Hands, by deserting me, are sprinkled;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207741:17"/>or by acting and consenting to my Death, are imbrued with my Blood. The Will of God hath confined and concluded mine; I shall have the Pleasure of dying without any Pleasure of desired Vengeance. This,</hi> I think, <hi>becomes a Christian to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Enemies, and a King towards his Subjects.</hi> And he breaths a seraphick Love to his Adversaries elsewhere. <hi>The Trophies of my Charity will be more glorious and durable over them, than their religious Rebellion and ill managed Victories over me.</hi> Mark his admirable Patience in see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Court made a <hi>Calvary. O my Soul! Think not that Life too long and tedious, wherein God gives thee any Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, if not to do, yet to suffer with such Christian Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Magnanimity in a good Cause, as are the greatest Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Lives, and the best Improvements of our Deaths.</hi> Farther, in the Language of his own Soul in Solitude, his Christian Courage and Patience sound in a sweet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort. <hi>The Assaults of Afflictions may be terrible, like</hi> Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son<hi>'s Lion, but they yield much Sweetness to those that dare to encounter and overcome them; who know how to over-live the Witherings of their Gourds without Discontent or Peevish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, while they may yet converse with God.</hi> All his <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishment</hi> was incomparable, and the King of Terrours could not un-king him of Meekness and Vertue: His Charity was as <hi>unparallel'd</hi> as his <hi>Case</hi> was to die; his Heroick Spirit and Greatness of Mind in forgiving a <hi>prosperous</hi> Injustice was as unimitable, as it could be none but the Result of his own Goodness. Now the Devil's raised, here's the Spirit of Contradiction: What a Stir is here with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? A Brat which King <hi>Charles</hi> must <hi>Father</hi> (forsooth) because it looks like him. What Noise with this great <hi>Diana</hi> of Kingly Wisdom and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence</hi> upon the Stage of Infidelity? He hath an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to Mobb upon that, and its very likely <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207741:18"/>Ghost conjured him to a disbelief of its <hi>supposed</hi> Princely Authority. The Book must be Dr. <hi>Gauden's,</hi> and the truest Pourtraicture of his Majesty was really drawn upon the Scaffold.</p>
            <p>One would have thought the <hi>Vindiciae Carolinae</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a Person of Primitive Learning and Integrity, might have disabused him, and undeceived him of the <hi>Bubble,</hi> satisfactorily proving it to have been the genuine product of that Royal Brain; and he must be an otherguise Man than Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> who now Controverts the <hi>Legitimacy,</hi> or so much as surmises the <hi>Spuriousness</hi> of its Birth. King CHARLES lives <hi>dimidiate</hi> in his rare Book, as poor <hi>Ovid</hi> was <hi>parte su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstes,</hi> by leaving his <hi>Tristia,</hi> as well as Family to the City from which he was banished; and those who do not Creed Him to be the Author of it after so <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Conviction,</hi> it is but reasonable to suppose, are grieved that he should yet Breath so lively after his last <hi>Farewell,</hi> and plead his Cause so learnedly after his direful Execution <hi>indicta causa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Author could heartily doom it to an Archive of Heretical Legends, or <hi>Catalogue</hi> it in <hi>Brown</hi>'s <hi>Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liotheca Abscondita,</hi> and wish it no where to be found but with <hi>Homer</hi>'s <hi>Batrochomyomachia,</hi> or the <hi>Homerican</hi> Battel between <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Mice,</hi> neatly described upon the <hi>Chizel-bone</hi> of a large Pike's Jaw. It is the Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of that <hi>gang-a,</hi> for whom there was most justly neither <hi>Rythm,</hi> nor no more <hi>Ben. Johnson</hi>'s Reason, than <hi>Swing-a Swang-a;</hi> and I would to God it did not only <hi>Reflect</hi> the <hi>ugliness</hi> of their Principles, but make him also (according to the Story of the <hi>Cock</hi> and the <hi>Glass</hi>) fall out with his own Picture. Can I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Martyrdom engraven so deep on the Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207741:18"/>Hearts of those implacable and impenitent Adversaries to Monarchy and present Majesty, as that the <hi>Teeth</hi> of Five and Forty Years-time hath not <hi>eaten</hi> out the Characters, and smooth'd it like the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's <hi>Tabula rasa,</hi> to inscribe another Rebellious Usurpation upon, since this Miscreant would <hi>gag</hi> up the <hi>remembrance</hi> of it, and have us like Turkish Mutes, to <hi>secret</hi> that Sin? In this he follows the <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps</hi> of the Blood-Hound <hi>Hewson,</hi> promoted from Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to Colonelling, who, <hi>upon an Hosannah of a shout raised by the Loyal Party at his Trial and no Trial,</hi> Blessed be your Majesty, God grant you to Reign long over us; God bring your Enemies under your Feet; <hi>presently drew up his armed Crew, and bad them give Fire upon the Naked Innocents, if any more they prayed for the King,</hi> p. 8. <hi>Paraphrase upon those Royal Legacies in his Majesties most Christian and Dying Speech.</hi> This was the <hi>Funeral Scene;</hi> Ambitious Desires and <hi>Blood-thirsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> produced <hi>mortal</hi> Enmities; and <hi>Pride</hi> in Triumph led <hi>Humility</hi> in Obedience to Martyrdom: The <hi>Horns</hi> of Covetous Men's designs pushed off the Crown, and it tumbled into a Protector's Lap; and let this <hi>feral</hi> Presbyter <hi>chew</hi> the Cud upon this, that though they put an immature Period to his Life, and brought his Body to the sad Catastrophe of being interred with an ignoble <hi>Hic jacet,</hi> whose living Bravery and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and Applause, the <hi>whole World was not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:</hi> Yet his Name and Honour must survive those <hi>Exits</hi> in our Churches Commemoration to a Glorious Kind of Immortality; and the Czar of <hi>Muscovy</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting his Rigid and Cruel Fate with a Christian-like Frown, and Contempt on all the <hi>English Traffickers</hi> there, induces me to believe, that his Fame is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207741:19"/>and celebrated with a sort of Ubiquity. If the Report of his English Treatment could startle an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel or amaze a Pagan, methinks it should make a hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Fanatick <hi>boggle,</hi> or <hi>scare</hi> him out of his puritanick Wits.</p>
            <p>As for King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, his Restoration, I shall be as short and <hi>touchy</hi> upon it as my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>First then; Room for the Lord of Mis-rule: Make way for the Grand Master of the Order of Disorder and Non-conformity. Who dare justle Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery in its Pomp and <hi>Parade,</hi> or confront the <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarian Insolence</hi> of santastick Anarchy in the Lob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? The Upstart Candidate for <hi>Sovereignty</hi> must let the Parliament know what <hi>Westminster-Hall</hi> enacted in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second his Time, to detract from his unspotted Profession is <hi>aniented</hi> in the Courts of Heaven: The Act for the Attainder of several Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, guilty of the horrid Murther of his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 12. <hi>Car.</hi> II. c. 30. is repealed and <hi>reversed</hi> to his whole Intent and Purpose <hi>above,</hi> or in <hi>B—ss</hi>'s Meeting-House, and how comes it a few <hi>musty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> do still <hi>attaint</hi> and stick that Venial Crime on their <hi>Progeny,</hi> or a Proclamation did follow and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue <hi>Ludlow</hi> at the Heels to a kind <hi>Shoar,</hi> whence an auspicious <hi>Blast wafted</hi> him out of the <hi>Reach</hi> of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution; and Providence <hi>hoiseing</hi> the Sails, and sitting at the <hi>Helm,</hi> at once <hi>steer'd</hi> him to a Sanctuary, and convinc'd our Statists that he was <hi>predestinated</hi> neither to be drowned nor hanged? A severe <hi>Old Saying</hi> has it otherwise with a <hi>Gallows</hi> to him: However, when one is got out of the Clutches of the Law, it is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant pleading a divine or eternal <hi>Decree</hi> for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:207741:19"/>tacking about, and calling the House of Commons all the Malignants under the Sun. As the <hi>Surly Rogue</hi> that has been <hi>lick'd</hi> for a Fault, no soon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er escapes the <hi>Correction,</hi> but turns about, and says, Son of a Bitch, what do ye <hi>lick</hi> me for? Did I do such <hi>a thing,</hi> or such <hi>a thing?</hi> The King of Kings hath passed a perpetual Indemnity to the <hi>Offspring</hi> it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, for the wicked <hi>Perpetrations</hi> of their <hi>Caitif-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors</hi> with a <hi>non obstante</hi> to our past, present, and future Proceedings, and disannulled all our Allegations against their good old Principles of <hi>beheading</hi> and <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing:</hi> This is the peerless Importunity and the very would-be-at of my Author in decrying our keeping a Day of Humiliation with prophaner <hi>Flouts</hi> and <hi>Scoffs</hi> than <hi>Aerius ridiculed</hi> the Christian Severities. He is of an Aerian Kidney, and stresseth us with the same Strain of Humour and Libertinism: <hi>It is Jewish thus to keep Days of fasting by a Law; it is an inslaving your selves to a Yoke of Bondage: If I would determine to fast at all, I would fast what Day I pleased at mine own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi> But <hi>Epiphanius</hi> does equally reprimand them both, as he is quoted in the <hi>Rationale</hi> on the <hi>Common-Prayer. Who are the more Fools;</hi> Aerius, <hi>a silly Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Yesterday, still living with us, or we who observe this severe Discipline which our Fathers delivered us, which they received from their Fathers, and they from theirs; and so from the Apostles</hi> the <hi>Sanctity</hi> and Usage of <hi>Fasting</hi> must be derived as from the original <hi>Sources</hi> of primitive Christianity and pure Devotion?</p>
            <p>Secondly, He scoundrels the Thanksgiving-Day with no demurer or decenter Scurrility, abominating <hi>it</hi> as well as the other, and <hi>branding</hi> it as a Day of <hi>Revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness</hi> appointed after <hi>revolutionary</hi> Heats and incensed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207741:20"/>disquiets. The Thoughts of a Restoration glad me, and <hi>flutter</hi> my Soul; and indeed Fancy and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion must <hi>flag,</hi> or their <hi>biting Heights</hi> be <hi>loured</hi> when the Mind is overjoyed, the last <hi>Canto</hi> of <hi>Butler</hi>'s <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibras</hi> confirms as much: But let me ask him, was King <hi>Charles</hi> big with <hi>spightful</hi> Venom? Did he labour with <hi>Revenge?</hi> He is the first <hi>Broacher</hi> of that Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, and the first that brought any <hi>slander</hi> upon his Mercy and Clemency, into the World; I guess he hath an excellent <hi>Knack</hi> of <hi>Midwifry,</hi> and can as easily <hi>deliver</hi> a King of some unhandsom piece of <hi>Ill-nature,</hi> as a Fro is of her mis-shapen Sooterkin; I rather Opine himself <hi>conceives,</hi> and he would lay the <hi>Bastard-quality</hi> on the King.</p>
            <p>He <hi>Libels</hi> him at Random, and <hi>Raves</hi> any thing to Blemish and Smut his Reputation, Mercifulness, Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Mildness: The <hi>blackest</hi> Scandals of my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, are but so many <hi>Set-offs</hi> to the Beauty and rare Embellishments of his Mind, and make his Peaceable <hi>Will</hi> and Affections, appear with greater <hi>Dazle,</hi> and more <hi>diffusive</hi> Lustre, inasmuch as such <hi>Calumniators</hi> as he, I am apt to presume, never felt the Rigour of his Justice, or the greatest Fine of his <hi>Displeasure</hi> for the <hi>Offence.</hi> It is notoriously true, and verified by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation, that the success of the Round-Heads their Enterprizes, never <hi>Authenticated</hi> their Cause, nor did their <hi>short-liv'd</hi> Prosperity justifie their <hi>Gallantry</hi> in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulness; but their <hi>gracious</hi> Impunity, and the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others go <hi>Scot-free,</hi> was not rigorous, and the Kings Establishing them a Right and Property to, or an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disturbed Enjoyment of their Plunder, Sequestration-Fruits, and <hi>filching Acquests</hi> was not unmerciful I hope; ay, but at his <hi>Return</hi> from a forced <hi>Extermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:207741:20"/>into Foreign Parts, he caused to be Sung in Churches an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> over their most Traiterous Conspiracies, the armed Power of Usurping Tyrants, and their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable <hi>Perfidy</hi> and <hi>Inhumanity</hi> in the Effusion of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Blood, and stubborn Opposition to his Enjoying his own again, <hi>The undoubted Hereditary Soveraignty and Regal Authority over them:</hi> This was a Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and <hi>Vindictive</hi> Incivility. It forced them to <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite</hi> their Actions, and <hi>Dissimulate</hi> a Joy; they seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly could rejoyce and laugh home the Exile; but it was as if they had Eaten of the Sardinick-Herb to their Grief and Sorrow, and all their <hi>Counterfeit</hi> Jolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at re-instating him, was to <hi>out-noise</hi> their <hi>Shrieks</hi> for the last <hi>Gasp</hi> of a <hi>dying</hi> Usurpation: For how could their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Hands</hi> go together in receiving him, or cordially Congratulating his Majesty's Arrival and <hi>Investiture</hi> in the Throne, whom they had <hi>resisted</hi> with the strength of Arm, <hi>dint</hi> of Councel, and the <hi>keenest</hi> Sword of Injustice? How could they give any sincere demonstration of a <hi>joyful Allegiance</hi> or Subjection, and Obedience <hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Passive</hi> to that Prince whom they had kept at as great a <hi>distance</hi> as their Pikes could <hi>Push</hi> or Awe to, and whose Wills perhaps committed <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> when their <hi>Hands</hi> were <hi>Innocent.</hi> It was harder then for them to <hi>Personate</hi> Loyalty or Feign Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, than to extenuate their former <hi>Lapses,</hi> and <hi>Vizard</hi> their belligerant Ambitions: Their Posterity are still Skinning over, Extenuating, and Palliating those Old Sores: While the <hi>Gangrene</hi> of Rebellion is not to be Cured but with Cutting off; else the State-Chyrurgeon knows it will break out again, and <hi>Ʋlcerate</hi> afresh, threatning Mortality like an Infection, to all about it: It had been no Cruelty in the King to have probed it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207741:21"/>deeper, for every Candid Judge is well satisfied how disproportionable their <hi>Punishments</hi> were to their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts,</hi> and their sins not half-<hi>salved</hi> to an <hi>unrelapsing,</hi> or <hi>un-apostatizing heal</hi> of Repentance, when the Royal Physician was <hi>restored</hi> to his <hi>Diseased</hi> Kingdom: And yet he must be called an <hi>unmerciful Tyrant,</hi> and a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject-Oppressor;</hi> He might declaim against Toleration with as severe <hi>turns</hi> as he does against his Mildness, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Grace to Offenders; but Majesty must be Cavil'd at <hi>fas vé nefas vé; and</hi> (as the Learned Author of <hi>Matchiavel</hi>'s and <hi>Borgia</hi>'s Policies says) <hi>'tis the fashion of Fortunate Rebels to Feed the People with Shells and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Names, as if their bare Assertion could demonstrate to us</hi> (against all Experience) <hi>that it is Freedom to be Slaves to</hi> Quondam <hi>Peasants, and Slavery to be Subjects to a True and Natural Prince, and that the Scorpions of Anarchy, Aristocracy, or a free State, are far more tolerable than the single Rod of Loyalty: And therefore if the Prince be severe, he gives them</hi> Nero<hi>'s Brand, a Man kneaded up of Dirt and Bloud; if he be of Parts and Contrivance, he calls it pernicious Ingenuity: If he be mild and favourable to tender Consciences, he declaims against his</hi> Cunning and Trepanning <hi>Toleration. If he urge Ʋniformity and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in Divine Service, he Rails at his Superstition. And because there is no such Aequilibrious Vertue, but has some Flexure to one of the Extreams, he is very careful to publish the Extream alone, and to silence the Vertue.</hi> Every one knows whose Politicks those are which <hi>Indict</hi> a King for miscarriages Living, but to <hi>Arraign</hi> him of <hi>aukward qualities,</hi> and pestiferous, slaving, leud, or wicked <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments</hi> Dead, is much like the <hi>Barbarick Cambyses</hi>'s Cruelties and Indignities used to <hi>Amasis</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who untombed his very Carcass, and commanded it to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:207741:21"/>be <hi>burned,</hi> contrary to the Custom of the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Persians</hi> as well as Humanity. The <hi>Persians</hi> feared to Feed their God with Carrion; and let not us Christians give Drink Offering of Blood to ours any more. <hi>De mortuis nil nisi bonum,</hi> and if I add <hi>principibus</hi> too, it ought to be no <hi>impracticable,</hi> or immoral <hi>Apothegm</hi> for Christians. My Author's <hi>Tongue</hi> is no <hi>Slander,</hi> and it would <hi>degrade</hi> a Majesty to take notice of his <hi>ignominies,</hi> or to reckon them <hi>Scandalum Magnatum.</hi> It is a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched</hi> Loyalty that speaks King CHARLES II. a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchee, whom I cannot but Honour in the Dust, and Sing of in the Poet's <hi>Strain</hi> upon another Herse;
<q>
                  <l>"Cujus in Laudibus</l>
                  <l>"Pacis, Justitiae, Clementiae</l>
                  <l>"publicae celebrandis</l>
                  <l>"Nec fama loquax, nec ipsa mendax</l>
                  <l>"poterit esse Epitaphium.</l>
               </q> 'Tis true, a King's a Man, and as Mortal as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi> could <hi>Ode</hi> him or <hi>Pale-face</hi> him, and some Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons must voluntarily come, through Inadvertency fall, or be extorted from him, which confess frail Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and require a <hi>favourable Censure,</hi> or an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Interpretation; and I conclude with the unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced <hi>Statist. Iniqua in omni re accusandâ, praetermis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis bonis, malorum Enumeratio, Vitiorum{que} selectio; nam ne ullus quidem isto modo Magistratus vituperabilis non erit. 'Tis an unjust Way of accusing to omit the good Offices of a Prince, and so to select and publish only his bad, for by this means, no Magistrate shall be innocent.</hi> His Birth, as a Man, and I may say as a Prince too, on the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ninth of <hi>May,</hi> was a lucky <hi>Omen:</hi> His Nativity
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:207741:22"/>and Return on the same <hi>Day,</hi> like the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of two good Planets, presaged to our Land a lasting Peace, Plenty, Prosperity, and a continued or undisturbed Succession of the Royal Line, and my Author may tell me if he will, that such <hi>Bodings</hi> are sometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and fair <hi>Promises</hi> are not always performed: But our <hi>Exaltation</hi> then was but reasonable and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate to <hi>Io Poean</hi> the signal <hi>Deliverance</hi> of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and faithful People from deplorable Oppressions, Devastations, Divisions, and Popular Furies. Why is our Religion in this Point of common Gratitude for providential Kindnesses, Courtliness, Flattery, Popery, Pageantry? For no other reason but because the Tub's turned, the King goes to Chappel, and Presbytery was very near being <hi>rump'd</hi> or lectured out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Here he lays on with the old Drum-stick, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and <hi>trumps</hi> that Knave upon us again; He would gladly have us to march after his <hi>Beats.</hi> How can we <hi>Voluntier</hi> it when he presses us so hard? We read indeed the Name of Christ in the <hi>Van</hi> of his <hi>rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit,</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi> brings up the <hi>Reer;</hi> and let him take this <hi>Motto</hi> for his Colours: <hi>Ecclesiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine armamini &amp; contra Ecclesiam dimicatis;</hi> as I find St. <hi>Augustine</hi> quoted. We shall still follow what Bishop <hi>Sparrow</hi> hath observed to us, and believe <hi>That the Sanctification or setting apart of Festivals, is conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Purity of primitive Practice, as being a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that Thankfulness, and a Part of that publick Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which we owe to God for his admirable Benefits; for those Feasts of Joy, and holy Revels are (as the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and judicious Hooker says) the Splendour and outward Dignity of our Religion,</hi> whose Lustre, and redundant Light of <hi>Gospel-shine</hi> our <hi>Owl-ey'd</hi> Author cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207741:22"/>else I may esteem him one of those <hi>none-so-blind,</hi> that will not <hi>see.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>lethargick</hi> Soul which neither God's <hi>Mercy</hi> can allure, nor impending <hi>Menace</hi> awake to pious and solemn <hi>Emanations</hi> of extolling the <hi>one,</hi> and imploring his Aversion of the <hi>other:</hi> Acts of Wonder next to Prodigy and <hi>Miracle</hi> on these two <hi>Grand-Days</hi> should make <hi>Stories</hi> in our Church as well as <hi>Annals,</hi> as long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd as the World, and lasting as the <hi>Moon,</hi> which <hi>wains</hi> only to an <hi>Increase,</hi> and appears in a splendider Full again. Our hardened Impenitence for the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, and therefore the most inglorious <hi>Sins,</hi> and our Unthankfulness for the <hi>Blessings</hi> of our Deliverances both by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land</hi> are as <hi>circular</hi> and endless as the <hi>redeeming Bounty</hi> it self: But they are scarce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent those <hi>Straits</hi> should bound their Presumptions, and their swoln Grandeur must have a larger <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference;</hi> the narrow Limits of an <hi>Island</hi> pinch them in <hi>Scope:</hi> The Usurper's <hi>Pomeria's</hi> must be inlarged without <hi>Restitution</hi> or Repentance; our Impieties must be <hi>transplanted,</hi> and the <hi>State-Sinner launches</hi> out, careering it to <hi>Hercules</hi>'s Pillars, but knows none but a Death-Bed's <hi>ne plus ultra:</hi> Then Five or Six Foot of <hi>dishonoured Earth</hi> will contain the <hi>magnifico,</hi> and stop the <hi>blustering Jehu-driven</hi> Hector.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. G.</hi> G's Observations upon the <hi>Martyrdom</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation,</hi> are especial Instances and Proofs of what I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert concerning our <hi>unmindfulness</hi> of Deliverances, and our whiffling unconcernedness for such National Crimes as King-Hunting, Deposing, Scaffolding. <hi>Hunting,</hi> I mention; for had not Providence made the <hi>pack</hi> of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suers run <hi>Counter</hi> of the <hi>Game,</hi> or <hi>cast</hi> too far over the <hi>Loss,</hi> they had made no less <hi>Sport</hi> of seizing the Prince
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:207741:23"/>in the Royal-Oak, than of <hi>unearthing</hi> the <hi>Fox,</hi> or <hi>uncasing</hi> the <hi>Carrion</hi> with a Tantivee Who-o-o-up. His <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension</hi> 'tis Ten to One, had <hi>pitcht</hi> him at the height of their Scorn and Pinnacle of Injustice in their High-Court, one degree from a Martyr as he was from a Defender of the Faith. Thus our <hi>Humorist,</hi> and his singularity, would out-face Religion, would have had our Church-History of the Restoration, written only in the same Element through which <hi>King Charles the First</hi> sailed to his <hi>Hereditary Haven,</hi> full <hi>fraught</hi> with our Deliverance, where no <hi>track</hi> of the <hi>Story</hi> could be Legible in <hi>Water-Characters;</hi> would have had the <hi>Grave</hi> of the Martyr like <hi>Pompey's,</hi> without any <hi>Inscription</hi> to distinguish the Dust of his Glorious Body from his ignoble Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's, (if he be yet Dead, for let <hi>B.</hi> know it is queried) or to shew, <hi>Here lies murdered Charles. Hos voluit nes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cire dies,</hi> as <hi>Lucan</hi> sings: These are malicious <hi>Dog-days</hi> with him, and so cross or <hi>clouding</hi> to his <hi>perswasion,</hi> that he would Curse them out of the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> if he could, not allow them any difference from others in our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory or Esteem, in our Joy or Sorrow, and its probable <hi>Excommunicate</hi> them (for they use to <hi>Reprobate</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we <hi>Elect</hi> in any Sense) from all Society with the Year, as <hi>Job</hi> did his <hi>Birth-day: Let the day perish to all memory, let darkness, and the shadow of Death stain it, and let forgetfulness like a Cloud, dwell upon it,</hi> Job 3.3, 5. But when all this is said, that our Rubrick to dignifie <hi>those</hi> above the Common Heap of Days piled up in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack is Superstitious, and our Service on them Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, the <hi>Fool</hi>'s Bolt is not half shot. He offers Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the two King's <hi>good-names</hi> with his Slanders and Calumnies; He gives us a <hi>Martyrium famae,</hi> a Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Fame of both, as well as of the Life of One.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:207741:23"/>Reputation is the preciousest Jewel about us all, <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Peasant,</hi> and as Rich and Dear as any in the Diadem to the meanest, so that he's the Notoriousest Thief that Robs us of it. What Key of Reserve can a Monarch put in the inside against the <hi>black-art-devices</hi> of such <hi>pick-locks</hi> of his Credit, Goodness, or Justice? It is the sole Apology and Refuge of exquisite Impostors, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent or <hi>raree-show</hi> those Kings for Spectacles of Scorn and Infamy after their Deaths, whom they made Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres of Misery in their Lives: And I affirm, that my Author's Imputations, Scandalous as False, in saying the Martyr was <hi>Guilty, and that Justice was Executed on him,</hi> wound him as deep, as what <hi>killed</hi> his Body, in that which is next in value to the Soul, <hi>His Good Name.</hi> To such a palpable untruth, such a <hi>mendacium fenestra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which hath so many wide <hi>Windows</hi> for any to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, this <hi>unglost</hi> Answer will be most convincing and suitable, <hi>Petilianus dicit, ego n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go:</hi> which is <hi>Rhetorick</hi> enough to Confute a Thousand bold-fac'd <hi>Liars,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>— Nam quis iniqui</l>
                  <l>Tam patiens Hominis, tam ferreus ut teneat se?</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Juv. Sat. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="note">
               <pb facs="tcp:207741:24"/>
               <head>THE Postscript-Advertisement.</head>
               <p>I Have omitted a Scholastick Discussion of my Author's Notions with submission to our Learneder Divines, confining my Thoughts to a bare Remarque upon his Arguments, which I hope is enough to unhood some Persons more Hawk-sighted in Divinity than my self, to Fly at him with an abler Quill, and a stronger Wing of the Church.</p>
               <p>Hereunto I have added a Dormant Piece, Printed about 1650. the awaking whereof in a New Edition does even <hi>Present,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, times past, and pourtrays the ghastly Shapes of Presbyterian Policies against our Church and Monarchical State, with none of the insipidest Touches: It is Ingenious, Laconick, and hath abundance of Salt in it. I did not snatch it out of the devouring Jaws of Moths and Worms, that it might live a Malefactor, or Malecontent in these Times; for it is so far from Tottering
<pb facs="tcp:207741:24"/>their present Majesties Crown, or detracting from their Government or Settlement, that it rather Consults how to Rivet them in the Throne, and Fix them against the Shock and Assaults of such Furious Assailants or Assassines, as the Presbyterians can Attempt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:207741:25"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207741:25"/>
            <head>A NEW DISCOVERY OF Old England, IN Certain Contemplative Observations upon the present Condition of this distracted Kingdom.</head>
            <p>POlicy and Allegiance makes a happy Prince in a discreet Subject; but Policy link'd to Disloyalty makes an unhappy Kingdom: The sad Truth is too apparent in our present Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs whom Obedience confines to the <hi>Prison,</hi> and Rebellion settles in the <hi>Chair. Episcopacy,</hi> like noble <hi>Uriah</hi> in the Front of the Battel, first struck at, by the Receipt of a mortal Wound, stain'd the Hands of the <hi>Infant</hi> Difference; since
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207741:26"/>whose Fall the adulterated Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been the Prostitute of a <hi>Synod,</hi> too too ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant to recompence her <hi>Vitiation,</hi> by contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her to Truth and Form: The <hi>fair one</hi> had some Spots i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Face to cleanse, but those in a Laver o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Blood have clouded the Glory of her Countenance. This unexplated Sin gave the Kingdom into the Hands of <hi>Men,</hi> whose Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may well vie Destruction with <hi>Israel</hi>'s Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence. The laborious <hi>Assembly,</hi> like their Forerunner <hi>Hacker</hi> (with Fan in Hand) sitting in Judgment upon the Scriptures, are as tedious in their Products as a <hi>teaming Elephant,</hi> disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening themselves once in three Years of some new <hi>Classis</hi> or Catechism, using their Mother (the Church) as pious <hi>Medea</hi> dealt with old <hi>Eson,</hi> kill'd him to renew his Youth, taking special Care that Popery may be wholly extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by picking out of the Ark all rotten and wormeaten Ceremonies, placing new and sound Doctrines of their own in the room, till in the end the Vessel (like that of Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi>) shall retain its former Name, though there be not a Stick of the first Composure in it. When it is thus <hi>rig'd,</hi> enter and set <hi>sail</hi> for Heaven, which, if we reach in such a Bottom, a <hi>Lapland</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207741:26"/>Witch sailing in a <hi>Sive,</hi> is not so great a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, though the same wicked <hi>Pilot</hi> steer both. Our industrious Re-edifiers of the Temple must work with one Hand and fight with the other, if they will raise the <hi>Fabrick</hi> in the new Model; a Piece in the <hi>Roundness</hi> altogether differing from wise <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>squarer</hi> Contrivements. I rather believe they are repeating the <hi>Babilonish</hi> Task, and that is the most probable by their Variety of Languages, one speaks <hi>Brownism,</hi> another speaks <hi>Barrowism,</hi> a third <hi>Anabaptism;</hi> one dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in Matter, another in Form, a third in both, from both the former; so that it is to be suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Misunderstandings will encrease to so passionate a Height, that after a confused Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Opinions (their prime Materials) those who understand one another (though under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by none but themselves) will sever and depart to <hi>Amsterdam, Geneva,</hi> and <hi>New England,</hi> their several Collonies.</p>
            <p>The second Act in this Tragedy of Peace, speaks injured <hi>Priam,</hi> the Safety of whose <hi>Troy,</hi> and self, was the lost <hi>Palladium;</hi> while the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle</hi> of the Lord, carried upon the Shoulders of the <hi>Priests,</hi> went before us, what Opposition of Schism could affront our <hi>Hoast?</hi> but now <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it ex Arca,</hi> and profaner Hands have been too
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207741:27"/>busie with our sacred Security. Our noble King (while Christian <hi>Loyalty</hi> was the constant Doctrine of that divine <hi>Oracle,</hi> Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) seem'd wall'd with Brass, and covered by the Veil of the <hi>Altar,</hi> from the poisonous Eyes of curious Malignancy, but now his naked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>protected Side lies open to the Attempts of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious <hi>Liberty,</hi> nothing wanting (in reference to their Inflictions) that may give a <hi>Complexion</hi> to his Sufferings, only his Alacrity in entertaining what their Hate can impose, shews him so far above their Malice, that he seems able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go more than their mischeivous Studies can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude; while he poor <hi>Prince of a Mole-hill</hi> (tho' Master of a Heart great as <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Ossa</hi>) like the <hi>King of true Beasts,</hi> entangled in the Toil (by some slight Improvidence of his own) scorns to fill the Ears of the World with Complaints and <hi>Roaring,</hi> but with Majesty repining to beg even Liberty it self, with Patience expects the <hi>Event</hi> of his <hi>Bondage:</hi> Thus <hi>Cesar</hi> threw his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over his Face and died perpetual <hi>Dictator.</hi> See what an undisturb'd Mildness his Face and Actions express, as if this <hi>Eagle</hi> were a <hi>Dove</hi> and had no Gall, no single Mischief thunders upon his Soul, the Injuries of a <hi>dear Wife,</hi> and a lov'd <hi>Issue</hi> come to crown his Patience, a Shock wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207741:27"/>the Resistance of so confirmed a <hi>Prince:</hi> Their own Eyes who have been Instruments in this must pay due <hi>Tribute</hi> to so sad a Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and weep that only this way is left 'em to their supposed Security: What does he suffer? Even that which would make Death in all its Horror to be courted by a carnal Apprehension. Dejected <hi>Job,</hi> in the Depth of Misery had triple Comfort, and though he chose the Dunghil for Repose was unconfined: Here 'tis Treason for the <hi>Son</hi> to beg his Father's Blessing, too much Liberty for the <hi>Father</hi> to be shut up from the Sight of the Children, and utterly impossible for the Council of <hi>Friends</hi> to reach his Ears, who being in himself so admirable a President, is to them the prime Object and Motive of Imitation and Perseverance.</p>
            <p>Who are his Enemies? Those (O the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happiness of Success in Treason) whose whole Help is <hi>Despair;</hi> since they are conscious they have sinned beyond Reconciliation, they are now resolved to make themselves clearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of Mercy,
<q>Una salus miseris nullam sperare salutem:</q> And Ills of this Nature cannot be safe without committing greater, therefore, like <hi>State-Fencers</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:207741:28"/>with the Sword of <hi>Reformation</hi> threatning to strike off petty Abuses at the Foot of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, they falsifie and have a care of your <hi>Head.</hi> The Design is not yet ripe for Action, the squinting <hi>Commonalty</hi> sees something, and a Northern <hi>Plea</hi> put in a <hi>Demur:</hi> However, to strike sure, the Affections of the Subject must be indirectly <hi>sounded:</hi> First remove his Throne out of the Peoples Hearts, and then one Man may do the rest. Nothing so effectual to this purpose as Detraction, and something must be spoken in <hi>Prologue</hi> to the intended <hi>Tragedy:</hi> Let it concern the Protestant Religion, and the Country questions it no further: The King hindred the Relief of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and their King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to due Obedience, dangerous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary: This relates to themselves, whom it behoves to oblige all they may to countenance Rebellion, guessing e're long they may want <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons.</hi> Next something monstrous enough to busie the Eyes of the World must be pretended, lest the Depth of their own projected Mischief should be leisurably inquired into. The <hi>Kid</hi> must be seethed in the <hi>Dam</hi>'s Milk, the <hi>Father</hi> died to leave the <hi>Son</hi> a Kingdom, the Son must not inherit because his Father's dead; who but such Artificers could have invented such an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207741:28"/>here <hi>Matchiavel</hi> does Homage. Did the <hi>King</hi> consent to violate his Father's Age? He is as far above their Question, as they are beneath their own Justification; endeavouring, like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Sons, to do no less to the Father of their Kingdom: Who, thus opprest, is happy in his <hi>true Miseries,</hi> while they are miserable in their <hi>seeming Happiness,</hi> having from his princely Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, Nobleness enough to create Fortitude, while they retain from their ambitious Attempts Uncertainty of Event, the Parent of Doubt and Fear. Should their Intentions move to his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, their own Mischief would <hi>halt,</hi> till their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention gave it <hi>Feet</hi> to overtake themselves: This cannot be unperceived, since already to avoid the easie Yoke of single Monarchy, they have subjugated themselves to the confused Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of as many <hi>Dictates,</hi> as the divided Army hath <hi>Brigades.</hi> A Body, whose Success was enough (had they been as ingenuous as fortunate) to have inrich'd them with a Repute durable as their now inseparable Infamy is like to prove; who, like the untamed <hi>Elements</hi> in the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Nature of Servants, were of use to their <hi>Employers;</hi> but their careless Masters have so long connived, that they may now change Names, being only formally what the other es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentially
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207741:29"/>are; to speak in a Martial Phrase, a <hi>Lieutenant Parliament</hi> to their <hi>General,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fairfax,</hi> poor <hi>Pigmalions,</hi> Slaves to an Image of their own making: The Counsel of War <hi>begets</hi> those Orders in private which the <hi>Country</hi> must <hi>Father</hi> in publick, though they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them with the Countenance of a <hi>Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> when he finds a Wenche's Maiden-head lap'd up in swadling <hi>Clouts</hi> in his <hi>Entry.</hi> Spight of all Contradiction, a Match must be struck between <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Independency,</hi> I fear while the <hi>Nuptials</hi> are celebrating, their Brother <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (as very <hi>Centaurs</hi> as themselves) will endeavour a Rape. And then, like <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>'s Earth-born Enemies, those <hi>Twin-Prodigies</hi> will by mutual Execution open a Passage through their own Bowels for injured Majesty to re-ascend the Throne. True Vertue is irrelative to either extream, and there is Hopes the <hi>House</hi> may stand while <hi>two</hi> contrary <hi>Winds</hi> strive to overthrow it. The <hi>Independent</hi> craftily cedes to the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and while he seems, by easie Compliance, to give ground, destroys his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suer: Thus a flying <hi>Parthian</hi> shoots backward. The <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> secure in his Flight, exposes his Breast to the unexpected Arrow, by the careless and open management of his Designs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207741:29"/>when both are fled or dead, the Kingdom will be without an <hi>Army.</hi> If the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> take the <hi>Cure</hi> in hand, one Poison may expel ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, something must succeed to cure the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, else the Mist that makes <hi>Independency vanish</hi> may make us <hi>wander:</hi> He that drowns in a Sea or a River, meets with an equal Ruine. The <hi>Crown</hi> we all know is at stake, for which the Souldiers and the States are casting Lots, it must fall to one of their Shares to rule; and let <hi>Aesop</hi>'s Frogs beware of the <hi>Stork:</hi> Yet, who so gains it shall find it like <hi>Nessus</hi>'s Shirt, when stripp'd over his Ears his <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Quarters</hi> will follow it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Countrey</hi> in the mean time, like pretty <hi>School-Boys,</hi> puff themselves out of Breath to mount those round <hi>Bubbles;</hi> whom, while they follow with their Eye and Admiration, if their unguided Feet stumble not to a further Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, their best Reward shall be the Loss of their Expences, and the Sight of <hi>nothing:</hi> This they begin to guess at, and would now be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be <hi>loyal,</hi> but that the Danger out-weighs their honest Desires,
<q>
                  <l>The Vulgar most to <hi>Cesar</hi> bends,</l>
                  <l>Yet with their Love their Fear contends.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:207741:30"/>
            <p>I could laugh to see them drink the <hi>King's Health</hi> by Signs, to the Encouragement of whose Ruine, so many Thousands of their <hi>peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary</hi> Hands have signed: A handsome Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, much like that Secret of Nature in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Magnus,</hi> where by spitting in that Fist with which you struck, the Pain of the inflicted <hi>Blow</hi> shall immediately cease.</p>
            <p>Well, let the Houses proceed, but this by the way, should the Train take Fire, and blow up the <hi>King, Power,</hi> and <hi>Person,</hi> look upon the <hi>Series</hi> of his <hi>Progeny,</hi> and this is no Security to the <hi>Machinators,</hi> but the expected <hi>Sun,</hi> instead of shining with Serenity upon the Kingdom, will become a Blazing <hi>Commet,</hi> threatning Fire and Sword. I hope better, and believe the wisest of them, like expert <hi>Generals,</hi> keep their Ground until their <hi>Carriages</hi> march off: Some petty <hi>Voters</hi> that pin their Resolve upon unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated Event; have not perhaps the Discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to perceive their own Danger or the <hi>Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances</hi> of their wiser Fellows. Let them consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Condition, and find themselves misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, since their whole Safety lives in the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an <hi>hired Army;</hi> especially when they know themselves so loath to pay the <hi>Hire</hi> of their own
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207741:30"/>
               <hi>Security:</hi> If the <hi>King</hi> may be mewed up, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier fooled, and the Scots blandish'd till the Houses are finished at <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed <hi>Angels</hi> flown to rest on the Bank beyond the Water, then all that can will skip to scape the <hi>Collar.</hi> 'Tis thought this <hi>Summer</hi> will ripen the Fruit, and those glorious <hi>Apples</hi> of <hi>Sodom</hi> drop from the Tree: If Heaven restore the <hi>Gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> to his Charge and Care, there will be <hi>lopping</hi> and <hi>throwing</hi> into the Fire; if not, the Soil will prove too <hi>rank</hi> for a settled Peace to <hi>flourish</hi> in. From their own Sins and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; we derive some Hopes from the Justice of our Cause, we second those and the <hi>Indispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Country towards their Injunctions, gives a further Confirmation: Who, though they enjoy some Immunity in their Silence; yet, as in their own <hi>Curs</hi> their not <hi>barking</hi> is not an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of their want of <hi>Teeth,</hi> happily they are in a <hi>Pinfold,</hi> and the hovering Army (though more like <hi>Wolves</hi> than <hi>Shepherds,</hi> awe them with a <hi>Whistle,</hi> but the Nature of those <hi>Flocks</hi> are like that of an immured <hi>Torrent,</hi> which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once found the least <hi>Rimula</hi> of Emission, pursues it to a perfect <hi>Enlargement.</hi> Should the <hi>North</hi> summon their <hi>Guards</hi> to an Employment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207741:31"/>some bold <hi>Dux Gregis</hi> or other, would lead the way, and then <hi>Ruit Vulgus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Vengeance, with a Motion swift as Injury can wish (through all the <hi>Foils</hi> and <hi>Doubles</hi> of Pretence) prosecutes the guilty <hi>Game</hi> in open <hi>View:</hi> Whose faint Evasions promise to Justice a sudden <hi>Attach</hi> of her expected Prey. Our <hi>State-Actaeons</hi> being (by looking with too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar an Eye upon Divine Majesty) transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a <hi>Chase</hi> for their own <hi>Scotch Beagles,</hi> who know not their once <hi>Masters</hi> in their newly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed <hi>Independent Shape.</hi> The <hi>Cavalier</hi> has been long at a <hi>Fault,</hi> but hearing the <hi>Cry</hi> renew, joyns Throats with the <hi>Covenant,</hi> a deep mouth'd <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound</hi> in a loud Pursuit: If the Blandishment of a <hi>Dominum cognoscite vestrum,</hi> in the late <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> cannot prevail to a Regard, the last Act must be like the Fall of an <hi>Eremanthean Boar</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt Security by a desperate Use of the <hi>Tusk</hi> and <hi>Sword;</hi> the only mischeivous Means to crown the unnatural Process with a <hi>Brutish</hi> Period. If the <hi>Scot</hi> be not too covetous to be honest, the next Scene is <hi>shifting,</hi> but give me leave to doubt the Reason of their <hi>Distance</hi> to proceed from the <hi>Taste</hi> of those <hi>Sweets,</hi> which the unwearied Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy of our <hi>Collector</hi>'s Industry here hath so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made them Fellow-<hi>Sharers</hi> in; I doubt they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207741:31"/>have the Discretion of making their Hire an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and can, like those,
<q>Qui noverant secreta domus atque inde timeri;</q> fright the <hi>Parliament</hi> when they please into a Compliance, by the <hi>Bug-bear</hi> of <hi>advancing;</hi> their <hi>League</hi> with <hi>France,</hi> and the Sense of that Honor which they exposed in delivering up his <hi>Majesty,</hi> who fled to them for <hi>Protection,</hi> may somewhat incline them to Motion: It would be as strange as grateful, should those <hi>Northern Blasts</hi> (which have hitherto breathed nothing but <hi>Barrenness</hi> and <hi>Sterility</hi> upon <hi>England</hi>) come hand in hand with our hopeful <hi>Spring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that rides upon the Wings of the Wind, can (if he please) make this <hi>Boreas</hi> a <hi>Zephire,</hi> to them a <hi>Storm</hi> that hate the <hi>King,</hi> to those a <hi>Calmy Fanning Refreshment</hi> that love him and the Peace of his <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>